<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Iesuites gospell: vvritten by themselues. Discouered and published by W. Crashaw, B. of Diuinity, and preacher at White-chappell</title>
            <author>Crashaw, William, 1572-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844712</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844712</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1444:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Iesuites gospell: vvritten by themselues. Discouered and published by W. Crashaw, B. of Diuinity, and preacher at White-chappell</title>
                  <author>Crashaw, William, 1572-1626.</author>
                  <author>Sribanius, Carolus, 1561-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second impression</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[12], 106, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop, and are to be sold at his house, being the next house to Saint Annes Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reprints, translates, and attacks a Latin poem on the Virgin of Halle in "Amphitheatrum honoris", 1606, by Clarus Bonarscius, i.e. Carolus Scribanius.</note>
                  <note>With an epistle to Sir W. Cokayne, Lord Mayor, and others.</note>
                  <note>First word of title is xylographic.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Some running titles read: The Iesuits gospell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Legends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scribanius, Carolus, 1561-1629 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> IESVITES GOSPELL: VVritten by themſelues. Diſcouered and publiſhed by <hi>W. Craſhaw,</hi> B. of Diuinity, and preacher at White-chappell. <hi>The ſecond Impreſſion Corrected and enlarged by the Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Bernard Alsop, featuring a head with an exotic head-dress and pendulums hanging at each side (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Bernard Alſop,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the next houſe to Saint <hi>Annes</hi> Church 1621.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR <hi>William Cockaine,</hi> the now Lord Maior, and Sir <hi>Francis Iones,</hi> Lord Maior Elect; of the ancient and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable City of <hi>London,</hi> and to the reuerend and <hi>renowned aſſembly, the Court of Aldermen.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>The ſpirit of Wiſdome, Truth Zeale, and vnity, be multipied.</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well knowne to the learned, and many your ſelues right Honorable, &amp; Worſhipful, that the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> (the Popes beſt and deareſt ſonnes) haue not yet troubled the world a hundred yeeres: for the Pope that to his owne hurt excommunicated <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. &amp; againſt his will called the conuentikle of <hi>Trent,</hi> eſtabliſhed alſo the order of the <hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Paul the 3. in the yeare 1540. allowed and eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bliſhed the order of the Ieſuits, being begun by theſe 10. named in the Bull. <hi>Ignatius Loyal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Petrus Faber, Iaco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Laynes, Claudius Iai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Paſcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Broet, Franciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Xauie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Alphon. Salmeron Simon Rodericus, Ioanne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Coduis. Nich. Bobadilla.</hi> &amp; reſtrained their num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber to 60. but 30. yeare after in another Bull h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> inlarged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny as they could get.</note> what their order is, what their vowes be, and what their Religion, you may know out of the booke called the <hi>Ieſuites Rule.</hi> What ſeruice they haue done their Maſter the Pope, all men gueſſe, wiſe men know, and all Nations in Chriſtendome feele to their paine, more or leſſe. And how ſenſible the Pope is of their ſeruice, apeares in that the firſt 5. Popes in their time, in recompence therof, haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed no leſſe then 36 <note n="b" place="margin">See the book calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Regula Ieſuitica<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
                  </hi> print<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at <hi>Rome,</hi> 1580. and ſine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at Lyons, and obſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wiſely ſome of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rules, and you ſhall find that the preſent ſtate, of a great part of Chriſtendome is a large coment vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the Ieſuites rule.</note> Buls or Charters of Priuiledges vpon the ſociety (beſides ſome which we ſhal neuer know of) euery one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firming or inlarging another, and the later yeelding more ample graces and fauours then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: Now if in their firſt 40. yeres, (being the time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their infancy) they were able to deſerue ſo well, what ſeruice may we thinke haue they performed, and
<pb facs="tcp:9548:3"/> how great thanks haue they receiued of the latter popes in theſe laſt 30. yeeres. of their age, when they are come to ſtrength and ripeneſſe: for tho <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. <note n="c" place="margin">See the book called Literae Apoſtolicae, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Inſtitutio confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio &amp; priuilegia. ſoc, Ieſu continentur: prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Rome 1587.</note> (being as wicked &amp; wily as themſelues) perceiuing their plots, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering their deepeſt drifts; vſed them accordingly, and not only gaue them nothing he could keep from them, but intended alſo <note n="d" place="margin">Watſon in his quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libers, confeſſeth as much, but this matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath better proofe then Watſon.</note> the reſtrayning or rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating of their order (had not they done as much for him, as he entended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) yet he and <hi>Paul</hi> the 4. only excepted (for it was ill halting before 2. ſuch cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) they can hardly name a Pope that liued a yeere of whom they receiued not ſuch fauours, as may well teſtifie to the world the great account the Pope makes of them. And will you know the reaſon? their <hi>deuotion,</hi> their <hi>doctrine,</hi> &amp;. their <hi>deedes,</hi> do merrit it at his hands: what their particular deuotion to the Pope is, appeares by the vow which they (aboue all other: <hi>Regulars)</hi> make to the Pope of preſent and abſolute obedience <note n="e" place="margin">See the book called Conſtitutiones Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Pontif. per Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum Matthaeum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duni 1588, amongſt the Conſtitutions of Paul the 3. in the third con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ution, pag. 305. there be the words of this vow</note> to do whatſoeuer he ſhould command them, to goe whetherſoeuer he ſhould ſend them, to Turkes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidels, Heretickes, without excuſe, denyall or delay. Their <hi>deedes</hi> for the Pope are anſwerable to their deuotion towards him, for theſe 50. yeeres haue they vpheld Popery <note n="f" place="margin">Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue diuers Popes confeſſed in the pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Buls granted to the Ieſuits, eſpecially Paul the 3. in his third Bul anno 45. &amp; in his 5. an. 49. &amp; Iulius the 3. in his firſt, and Pius the 4. in his firſt, and others.</note> as far as wit and learning, nay as farre as craft and cruelty can vphold it, which without them had vtterly r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inated (as not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it ſhortly will, and they with it, doe what they can) They haue pickt out the fineſt yong wits of the world, <note n="g" place="margin">theſe be their words in the regula Ieſuitica, cap. 3. reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. Inepta turba ad inſtitutum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrú admitti non poteſt.</note> and ſo trained them vp, that the Pope ſhal neuer want inſtruments to kill Kings, to ſubuert ſtates, to patch vp a peace, or to breake leagues as he thinks good: let but the Diuel deuiſe it, &amp; the Pope command it, and forthwith the Ieſuits will find him ſhall execute it.</p>
            <p>Moreouer what they haue attempted for the Pope, in England, Scotland, Hungary, Bohemia, Venice, and the Low-Countries: what they haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for him in France and Poland: how they rule &amp; raigne in Spaine &amp; Italy, who ſo blind as ſees not? Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s this all they haue done? Nay they ſcatter themſelues like Locuſts ouer all the world; and with the Frogs of Hgypt creepe into <hi>great mens houſes,</hi> and firſt ſeduce the ſilly women, and not ſo content, worke themſelues into the fauours, at leaſt into the Courts, Coaches, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Princes; &amp; diuing into mens conſciences &amp; counſels, by the ſtratagems of their confeſſion, and after into their purſes &amp; eſtates, by benefit of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, <note n="h" place="margin">many orders of Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers &amp; many popiſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue complained of the Ieſuites, in theſe eſpects.</note> &amp; laſtly into the conceits of the Vulgar, by an hypocriticall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity and diſſembled deuotion, they haue hereby gained more to the Pope their Lord and Maſter, then all the Romiſh Clergie in the world beſides: But is this yet all? nay, that the Pope may ſeeme to haue a good cauſe, and not to do all things by a ſtrong hand, they haue taken a courſe to make all writers in the world ſpeake for him: (an attempt which the former ages ſuſpected not, and the future will ſcarce beleeue) for ſome bookes they prohibite and extinguiſh and make it damnable to open them: the reſt be they old or new, printed or manuſcript, they alter adde and take away <note n="i" place="margin">For the firſt ſee their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook called, Index li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rorum prohibitorum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et out by authority of ſeuerall Popes. And for the ſecond, ſee the books called, Indices librorum expurgandorum, printed in Belgia, Italy, and ſpaine, as alſo Gregorij. Capuccini, Enchiridion Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icum, and Poſſeuine the Ieſuit his apparatus ſacer.</note> till they haue
<pb facs="tcp:9548:3"/> ſuckt out the ſweeteneſſe, and purged out all the goodneſſe, and taken out all teſtimonies of the truth: inſomuch as if they had not been warily watcht, followed by the footeſteps, and taken euen in the manner, they had not left one booke allowed in the world, that had not ſpoken for the Pope: Such worthy workemen are the Ieſuits, that thoſe good &amp; worthy men which prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and wrote againſt the Pope, whilſt they liued, their Sermons &amp; writings ſhall teſtifie for him, long after they are dead: But why doe I offer to diſcerne or or diſcouer Ieſuites practiſes? alas, I am too ſilly and too ſhallow, I confeſſe I know them not, and yet I am ſorry I know ſo much: my hope is that their beginning, their breeding, their feeding, their growth, their greatneſſe, their rules and religion, their plots and practiſes, their murders and maſſacres (being ſuch as makes England baniſh them, Denmarke deteſts them, Venice wil none of them, Italy, is weary, &amp; France is ſick of them, and Spaine it ſelfe is iuſtly iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) My hope I ſay is, that a perfect diſcouery of all theſe will be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome that may make perfect that ſmall beginning &amp; foundation, which in 2. little bookes is already laid in that kind <note n="k" place="margin">Aphoriſmi doct. Ieſuitie. De abſtruſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus ſtudijs Ieſuitarum</note> meane time for the better vncaſing of this Foxe, and vnmasking this Hypocrite, let me come to that which is neerer to my Element, &amp; conſider a little of their doctrines, which is the third meanes by which they haue deſerued ſo well of the Papall ſtate: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, I will ſay nothing but what I know, and what I dare referre and do ſubmit to your iuſt and iuditious cenſures, I ſay therefore that whereas the Romiſh Church is that <hi>ſcarlet whore,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Reu. 17. 1, 2. &amp;c.</note> and her Idolatries and ſuperſtitions the <hi>ſpirituall abominations with which ſhe makes drunk the inhabitants of the earth</hi> and that in this latter age her cup of abominations was almoſt drunke vp, and emptied euen to the dreggs: in this exigent and extremity theſe like <hi>Locuſts flye out of the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> to repaire the ruines of the Romiſh ſtate, and to fill her <note place="margin">Reuel. 9. 2.</note> golden Cup with a new ſupply of ſpirituall fornications: to which end they haue firſt reuiued many diuelliſh doctrines, halfe dead and damned in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, and what in former times were ſcarce muttered in corners by the worſt of their Predeceſſors, is now by them preached on the houſe tops: And ſecondly, not ſo content, the better to fill her cup with the very quinteſſence of moſt refined abominations: they haue hatched many horrible doctrines and helliſh opinions neuer heard of in the elder ages; which are ſuch excellent and exquiſite infections to a mans ſoule, that the purple Whoore hath willingly throwne away <note n="m" place="margin">Popery is much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred ſince the Ieſuites both in their ſeruice, as may bee ſeene in their Miſſals &amp; breuiaries: &amp; in their ceremonies, as appeares in their ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficale and ceremoniale comparing the old and new together.</note> a great part of her older druggs, to make roome for the new and more precious poyſons confected by the Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>Of the firſt ſort, and ſo of the ſecond, I dare be bold to giue you a taſte, though they bee mortall poyſons, becauſe I know you are armed with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes and precious preſeruatiues againſt them.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Of the firſt ſort are theſe.</head>
               <item>1 That an Image of God or Chriſt is to be worſhiped with <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, with the ſame ſame worſhip as God himſelfe: <note n="n" place="margin">So teach Gretſer &amp; Gregory de Valent, and ſay it is the common &amp; receiued opinion,</note>
               </item>
               <item>2 That God hath deuided his Kingdome with the Virgin Mary, keeping iuſtice to himſelfe but committing mercy to her.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:9548:4"/>
               <item> 3 That a man may appeale from Gods iuſtice to the mercy of the Virgin Mary. <note n="o" place="margin">Theſe two Biel and Bernardine de Buſt doe teach and Poſſeuine the Ieſuit, highly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mends thoſe very bookes.</note>
               </item>
               <item>4. That the Pope is ſuperior to the Emperor, not only in ſpiritual but euen in temporall things, &amp; ought to haue place and predence afore him <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o teacheth liber ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crarum ceremoniarum, Romane Eccleſie, which is highly commended by Bellarmine as Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinus alſo confeſſeth.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe and many others which ſcarce durſt peepe out in former times, are now by the Ieſuits made publike and plauſible doctrines, and being almoſt bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and forgotten, are by them againe reuiued.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Of the ſecond ſort.</head>
               <item>1 That God hath made the Virgin Mary partaker of his diuine power and maieſty, <note n="q" place="margin">So teacheth Hora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Turſellinus a Ieſuit.</note> as farre as he may.</item>
               <item>2 That a man ſhall oft time bee ſooner heard at Gods hand in the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Virgin Mary, then of Ieſus Chriſt. <note n="r" place="margin">So teacheth Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomus a Viſit. a Ciſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, and is allowed by Poſſeuinus.</note>
               </item>
               <item>3 That a man may equiuocate before a Magiſtrate. <note n="ſ" place="margin">So teach Azorius &amp; Tollet and all Ieſuits.</note>
               </item>
               <item>4 That Hereſie makes a man vncapable of a Kingdome, and makes him an Vſurper, that is otherwiſe a lawfull King <note n="t" place="margin">So teach Marianus Simancha, Bozius and others allowed by the Ieſuits.</note>
               </item>
               <item>5 That the Pope hath power not only to pronounce what is hereſie, but after that to depriue him of his Kingdome, and to diſpoſe of it as he thinkes beſt. <note n="u" place="margin">So teacheth Roſſeus and others allowed by the Ieſuits.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>With many other, not conuenient heere to bee perticularized which the former times neuer heard of, at leaſt in ſuch manner as now they be holden,</p>
            <p>But ſeeing they be all of two ſorts, either touching the crowne of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, or the crownes of Kings his deputies on earth, I will deſire you to be contented with one example of both ſorts. Concerning not ſuch Kings as make not themſelues ſlaues and harlots to the purple whore: thus teacheth a Ieſuit too well knowne in Eglnand.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="x" place="margin">See the book called Andrea Philopatris re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſio ad Edictum Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabethae ann. 91. ſect. 2 artic. 157. pag. 109. edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis aug. 1592. This man is Arthur Creſwell the Ieſuite.</note> It is the iudgement of all Catholike Diuines and Lawyers, and it is certaine, and <hi>de fide:</hi> that what Chriſtian Prince ſoeuer, doth apparantly fall from the Catholike Religion, and would alſo draw others with him, doth <hi>Ipſo facto</hi> forthwith fall from all right, title, place and power of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes or Dominions, by force both of Gods and mans law, and this before any ſentence be pronouced againſt him by the Pope: and that all his Subiects are free from the Oathes they haue made to him. And they may. nay they ought (if they be able) to put him downe and caſt him out from all gouernment, as an Heretike, an Apoſtate, and an enemy of God and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth &amp;c. And this doctrine is certaine, vndoubted and reſined &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alas that we ſhould liue to heare ſuch doctrine taught, eſpecially by an Engliſhman I but whereas he ſtiles himſelfe <hi>a Diuine and a Prieſt of Rome,</hi> wee thence conclude that he carried no ſuch learning with him out of England, but found it at Rome.</p>
            <p>Concerning Chriſt, that which I haue afore ſet downe is vile and wicked and ſuch as the elper world and miſty times of Popery would haue abhorred. But there is one impiety of late broched by one Ieſuit, and approoued by all, ſo horrible and hainous, as I want words to expreſſe it. <note n="y" place="margin">Clarus Bonarſeius a Ieſuit, writes it: Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine the Ieſuit in the name of all other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proues it.</note> But this I can ſay, it is ſuch as the world yet neuer heard of, ſuch as the ages paſt feared
<pb facs="tcp:9548:4"/> not, and the future will not beleeue: nay ſuch as we in theſe dayes would not beleeue of our very enemies, if the euidence of the fact made it not paſt all denyall and excuſe: for would a man imagine that thoſe who profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt aboue other men, ſhould conceiue of him, ſpeake to him, and play with him, as with a ſucking child in his mothers armes? Nay that is nothing, they make him an vnderling to a woman, and not his Perſon only but his bloud and merits, &amp; compare together his bloud and her milke, and vpon compariſon finds them ſo equall, that they mixe them together, and in the mixture finds the milke ſo excellent, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it afore the bloud, as a thing more precious, and with which, they may not be ſo bold as with the bloud of Chriſt, and feare not to affirme that the corruptions of our nature, and ſinnes of our ſoule are healed and holpen as well by her milke as Chriſts bloud. A blaſphemy whereat the Angels will ſhrinke, and the very diuels tremble, and yet no doubt wee ſhall finde Ieſuites will defend it.</p>
            <p>Hauing obſerued this blaſphemy 2. or 3. yeeres agoe, I held my tongue, expecting it would bee diſcouered and reproued by ſome that could doe it with more authority, but fayling of my hope, I long conceal'd my labours till now, that the neceſſities of theſe euill times doth force it from mee: I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do heere diſcouer it, and am bold to ſend it abroad vnder the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your honorable names, that ſo all the world may know the ſtate and gouernment of this honorable Citty, to be no approouers, but Cenſors and condemners of ſo horrible and hideous Atheiſme.</p>
            <p>I am therefore a ſuter to you all, in mine owne and the name of all my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Clergy of this City, that you looke well to the execution of the lawes, and yet rather againſt Popery then Papiſts: For it is the wicked Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery that makes our men Papiſts, and ill ſubiects to God and the King: The men would be good enough if the grounds of their religion were not wicked. Therfore we beſeech you haue care, that Iuſtice be ſo executed as rather the wickedneſſe of the Religion may bee rooted out, then the perſons puniſhed as in his ſtile, to be <hi>The defender and propogatur of the true Chriſtian Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Honourable and worſhipfull, vouchſafe to heare vs in this iuſt &amp; neceſſary requeſt, being no leſſe then your Religion craueth at your hands: The Clergy and Miniſtry of England are ſlandered by the Papiſts, that wee ſeeke their bloud, &amp; exaſperate the ſtate againſt them: but they do vs wrong it is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpating of Popery, not the bloud of Papiſts, that we ſeeke and ſue for: we pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty their perſons, and wiſh them rather all baniſhed then any executed, but we hate their hereſies, and wiſh them cenſured, condemned, and extinguiſhed as as they deſerue: This is the way fully to diſcouer Antechriſt, and to haſten his confuſion, for almoſt all Churches of Chriſtendome haue pronounced him Antchriſt, and his Religion Hereſie: And this is the ſure way to be free from treaſons, conſpiracies inuations, murders and maſſacres, from which (as you ſee) <hi>Denmarke</hi> by this meanes is defended, and many countries well freed as ſoone as they get free of Ieſuits: and by the contrary we ſee the miſerable
<pb facs="tcp:9548:5"/> accidents in <hi>France,</hi> to the amazement of the Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tian world: for when all the truth is known, &amp; the whole account caſt vp, the charge of thoſe foule facts the murders of 2. Kings, &amp; many more vnnaturall diſaſters, will lye vpon the vngodly poſitions of Popery: As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of <hi>Abner</hi> when he mourned for him, ſo may we much more of their laſt King, <hi>Know you not that a great man is fallen in Chriſtendome?</hi> Surely one of the greateſt many wayes that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome hath yeelded: It is full time to looke about you, when your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe is on fire, and the rather when Ieſuites teach this doctrine to be defined, and to be <hi>de fide,</hi> that <hi>ſubiects not only may but ought to take away ſuch Kings as he was,</hi> and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s (much more) is, and long may he ſo be: Nay long ſhall he be ſo if you take this and other courſes for exti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pating Popery: When you and other the Magiſtrates Eccleſiaſticall and ciuell ſhall begin ſeriouſly and effectually to do this, then Rome trembles, Popery ſhrinkes, Antichriſt frets, and the Ieſuits his darlings begin to looke pale, and hang downe their heads for their confuſion is at hand: for though they haue continued but iuſt. 70. yeares (not the halfe of many other orders) yet they muſt know that <hi>bloud-thirſty and deceitfull men ſhall not liue out halfe their dayes.</hi> And if they be not guilty of theſe 2. faults <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>deceit,</hi> wee will free them from all <note place="margin">How bloudy the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes be appeares in that this is their maxime im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>printed. Niſi religio Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therana, ferro &amp; igne tollatur, Eccleſia Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acem &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quilitatem habere non poterit See the booke called E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolarum Ieſuiticar. Libellus agab. Bariaco 99. in Epiſt. art 11. pag. 66. A great Image, whoſe glory was excellent) &amp; fourme terrible, whoſe head was of fine gold, his breſt and armes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uer, his belly &amp; thighs of braſſe, his leggs of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, his feete part of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, and part of clay. Daniel. 2. 31. 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inc dubium non eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocietatem noſtram vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubito caepit, it a ſubito <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>territuram qui quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em peius ruit.</note> faults: but if they bee, and that aboue all men, then take heede you Ieſuites, that this your 70. yeare, be not a diſmall and fatall yeare vnto you, and that our Dauid and Moſes do not pronounce of you, <hi>the yeeres of your continuance are threeſcore and ten, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be ſo mighty and ſo crafty, you may hold out till foureſcore, yet ſhall your life be nothing but ſorrow and miſery</hi> (as you haue deſerued) <hi>and quickly ſhall ye be cut off and vaniſh away:</hi> and if this Prophecy like you not, take one of your owne. In the yeere 83. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Ieſuite preached at Auſpurg, and his text being, <hi>we are made a ſpectacle to God, Angels, and the world:</hi> in his Sermon he compared the Ieſuites order to the Image, which Nabuchadnezzar ſaw in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>aulo. Our Father <hi>Ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atius</hi> (ſaith hee) is the <hi>golden head,</hi> together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith thoſe that liued with him: but when the firſt 10. fathers were dead, others followed, nothing ſo good as the firſt, and theſe were the <hi>breſts and armes of ſiluer.</hi> Then our ſociety being inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from 60. to many hundreds, it grew in <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> but decayed in <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and then moſt of them were idle bellies; and ſuch whoſe God was their belly, and theſe are <hi>the bellies and thighes of braſſe:</hi> and then ſtill growing line number, and falling into more voluptuousneſſe and carnalty, they were ſo drowned in pleaſures, that their hearts were hardned againſt all good counſell and admonitions, theſe were the <hi>legs of Iron:</hi> and laſtly many of vs are ſuch as tho they liue in our golden ſociety, yet they are altogether earthly minded men: and theſe be the <hi>feete of Clay.</hi> Hereupon (ſaith he) <hi>It is out of all doubt that as our ſociety ſuddenly begun, ſo ſhall it ſuddenly come to nought, ſeeing it dayly falls from ill to worſe:</hi> O my brethren ſaith he, ſuch a ſpectacle are wee made! Now therfore leaſt this Image of ours be broken in pieces (as that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was) we muſt goe to our father <hi>Ignatius,</hi> that good Alchimiſt, and learne of him how we may be transformed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clay and yron into gold againe: let
<pb facs="tcp:9548:5"/> vs therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> goe into the furnace and purge our ſelues: Thus farre the Ieſuites Sermon: But if their liues be lookt at for the 30. yeares ſince he ſpake, wee ſhall find that either they could not yet ſpeake with <hi>Ignatius,</hi> or if they did, he was no true Alchimiſt, but a quackſaluer, and could not direct them, or if hee did, the furnace is to hot, for all the world can witneſſe they are not purged from their ambitions, couetouſneſſe, treacheries, bloud, cruelty, deceitfulnes, &amp; all carnalties, but haue grown on riper in all rottennes, and more fit to be driuen and daſht in pieces: but if the Ieſuits wil follow their Allegory ſtil, and aske vs how they can be broken, for that Image was broken with a <hi>ſtone cut out without hands,</hi> I anſwere, ſeeing they haue found the Image, I can find the ſtone. (a) Chriſt is the great and chiefe corner ſtone who can and will grind to powder all that exalt themſelues againſt him. And was cut out without hands, euen made man without the helpe of man.</p>
            <p>But by and vnder him, his holy religion ſetled in this Iland: in England, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a woman, in Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, vnder a child, is a ſtone cut out without hands; for it was the Lords doing, &amp; was maruelous in the eyes of all the world: Morouer, his Maieſties comming to vs, and ſetling with vs, and vniting of vs, with our ancient Brethren and neighbours of Scotland, who but God could haue done it in that peaceable and bleſſed manner as it was: Sure it was a ſtone cut out without hands of man: It was the Lords owne worke, all the world excepting the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſin, the Ieſuits, &amp; their wicked adherents reioyced to ſee it. Know therfore you Ieſuits, that this ſtone cut out by God, euen this true faith profeſſed and ſetled in this Iland, and this gracious King whom God hath ſent vs to be the zealous defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of that faith, ſhal caſt down the <hi>great excellent and terrible</hi> Ieſuiticall <hi>Image. ſmiting him vpon the feete of yron and clay, and breaking them to pieces, till your yron and clay, and braſſe and ſiluer, &amp; gold,</hi> (if you haue any left) <hi>be broken altogether, and become like chaffe of the ſommer flowers, and the winde ſhall carry you away till there be no place found for you.</hi> And then <hi>the ſtone that ſmote the Image,</hi> euen this holy Religion now profeſſed &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in England, <hi>ſhall become a great mountaine,</hi> that is, ſhal be enlarged, <hi>and fill the whole earth</hi> which as we are aſſured will be true of our Religion (which is the glory of our land, and that which vnites vs to Chriſt the true corner ſtone) ſo we doubt not, it ſhall be alſo true of our Soueraigne and his ſeede, that they after they haue broken the Ieſuiticall Image, ſhal againſt Gog and Magog, and Antechriſt, and all his Adherents, become a great and ſtrong mountaine, and fill the whole earth with the glory of their renowned deedes: and let earth and heauen ſay Amen, with the honorable religious and loyall Citty of London, and all good Chriſtians: and with</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humbly deuoted ſeruant in Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>W. Craſhawe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:6"/>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9548:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE POINTS OF NEW</hi> DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity contayned in this <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat the milke of <hi>Mary</hi> may come into compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>2 That the Chriſtian mans faith may lawfully take hold of both as well as one.</p>
            <p>3 That the beſt compound for a ſick ſoule, is to mixe together her milke and and Chriſt bloud:</p>
            <p>4 That the ſinnes and ſpirituall diſeaſes of the ſoule are cured as well by her milke as his bloud.</p>
            <p>5 That Chriſt is ſtill a little child in his Mothers armes, and ſo may be prayed vnto.</p>
            <p>6 That her milke and the merit and vertue of it, is more precious and excellent then Chriſt bloud.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:9548:7"/>
            <head>IN THE APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>THat no man, but a woman did helpe God in the worke of our redemption.</p>
            <p>2 That God hath made Mary partaker and fellow with him of his diuine Maieſty and power.</p>
            <p>3 That God hath diuided his Kingdome with Mary, keeping Iuſtice to himſelfe, and yeelding mercy to her.</p>
            <p>4 That a man may appeale from God to her.</p>
            <p>5 That a man ſhall oftentimes bee ſooner heard at Gods hands in the meditation of Mary, then of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:9548:7"/>
            <head>THE OCCASION <hi>OF THIS IESVITICALL Blaſphemy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>VSTVS LIPSIVS, a man of learning enough, but too much leuity, hauing run ouer all religions; &amp; at laſt ſet vp his reſt in <hi>Popery:</hi> fell in his declining and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting daies to open <hi>Idolatry:</hi> And as he neuer troubled himſelfe much with Chriſt in his life (whoſe very name a man ſhal ſeldom find in his books) ſo at his end, wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting matter (it ſeemes) to magnifie Chriſt, he writes 2 books in praiſe and honor of 2 Idols: namly 2 old rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or 2 new forged pictures of a woman with a child in her armes. Which muſt needs be taken for pictures of our Lady: Wherin the prophane wrerch bluſheth not to write, that at theſe 2 Images, there are more &amp; greater miracles wrought, then the ſcriptures ſpeake of to bee done by Chriſt himſelfe. A learned low-Country Diuine wondring that ſuch Owles durſt flie
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9548:8"/> abroad at Noone light, and ſuch trompery be ſet to ſale in theſe dayes of knowledge, wrote a ſhort re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proofe of the impieties vttered in the firſt of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bookes, which is:</p>
            <q>De Virgine Hallenſi.</q>
            <p>Wherein becauſe the Ieſuits were alſo touched, as being the fathers of ſuch fooleries, and the makers of thoſe bolts which ſuch fooles as <hi>Lipſius</hi> doe ſhoote: Thereupon a Ieſuit of <hi>Antwerpe</hi> calling himſelfe <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Bonarſcius,</hi> (but his true name being <hi>Carolus Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banius)</hi> taking vpon him in a Ieſuiticall pride, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall quarrell of the whole order of Ieſuits, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to defend their innocency, and their honor (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) againſt all the world: and to that end writes a book, and calls it, <hi>The great Theater of the Ieſuits honor.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Amphitheatrum Honoris. In quo Caluiniſtarum in Societatem crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones <hi>iugulatae.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Wherein, after many blaſphemies againſt Chriſt: ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies &amp; ſlanders againſt princes: all kind of lyes againſt our miniſters &amp; profeſſors: he comes at laſt to defend their friend <hi>Lipſius,</hi> and his legend of our Lady of Hall: And after he hath abuſed him that wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, with all deſpightful tearmes, and rayl'd moſt artificially, wherein he excels all other Ieſuits, <hi>(Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> excepted) as far as they, all other Papiſts: Hee makes a tranſition fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rayling on men to playing with God: and from diſgracing Princes to dallying with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9548:8"/> Ieſus Chriſt: and not onely defends the legend of <hi>Hall,</hi> written by <hi>Lypſius,</hi> but further to ſhew his owne deuotion, he makes a Poeme, not to the honour of God, or of Chriſt the Mediator: but to our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Hall</hi> and the child Ieſus. Wherein, whether the verſe be better or the matter worſe is hard to tel: But whether his deuotion therin is greater to a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or his blaſphemy againſt the blood of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, let the Chriſtian Reader Iudge, by the Poeme it ſelfe, which hereafter followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:9548:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>EX CLARI BONARSCII AMPHYTHEATRO</hi> HONORIS. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 356. <hi>editionis</hi> 2. 1606. AD <hi>DIVAM HALLENSEM,</hi> ET <hi>PVERVM IESVM.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HAEREO lac inter meditans, inter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cruorem</l>
                  <l>Inter delicias vberis, &amp; lateris.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <l>Et dico, (ſi forte oculos ſuper Vbera tendo)</l>
                  <l>Diua Parens Mammae gaudia poſco tuae.</l>
                  <l>Sed dico (ſi deinde oculos in vulnera verto)</l>
                  <l>O Ieſu, lateris gaudia malo tui.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <l>Rem ſcio. Prenſabo, ſi fas erit, Vbera dextra</l>
                  <l>Laeua prenſabo vulnera, ſi dabitur.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <l>Lac matris miſcere volo cum ſanguine nati:</l>
                  <l>Non poſſem Antidoto nobiliore frui.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <l>Vulnera reſtituent turpem vlceribus mendicum:</l>
                  <l>Teſta cui ſaniem radere ſola poteſt.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9548:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bera reficient I ſmaclem ſitientem</l>
                  <l>Quem <hi>Sara</hi> non patitur: quem neque nutrit <hi>Agar:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Illa mihi ad peſtem procul &amp; procul expungendam:</l>
                  <l>Iſta mihi ad long as eualitura febres.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <l>Ira vomit flammas, fumat que libidinis Actna?</l>
                  <l>Suffocare queo ſanguine, lacte queo.</l>
                  <l>Liuor in expleta rubigine ſaeuit in artus?</l>
                  <l>Detergere queo lacte cruore queo.</l>
                  <l>Vanus honos me perpetua prurigine tentat?</l>
                  <l>Exaturare queo ſanguine, lacte queo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <l>Ergo Parens &amp; Nate, meis aduertite votis:</l>
                  <l>Lac peto, depereo ſanguinem: vtrumque volo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <l>Paruule maternis medius qui ludis in vluis</l>
                  <l>Qui tua iam comples vbera, iam vacuas:</l>
                  <l>Quid me reſpectas obliqua tuentibus hirquis?</l>
                  <l>Roboris in Coelum nil habet Inuidia.</l>
                  <l>Saepe quidem dixti, noxis offenſus iniquis,</l>
                  <l>Tune meas mammas, Improbe, tune meas?</l>
                  <l>Nolo tuas, O nolo tuas Puer auree mammas:</l>
                  <l>Non ſum tam duri tamgrauis or is homo:</l>
                  <l>Sed tantum later is pluat vnica &amp; vnica ſtilla:</l>
                  <l>Et ſaltem à dextrae vulnere gutta pluat.</l>
                  <l>Si nihil è dextra vis impluere, implue laeua:</l>
                  <l>Si nihil è laeua, de pede ſanguis eat.</l>
                  <l>Si tibi non placeo vulnus mihi vulnera danto:</l>
                  <l>Mercedem danto vulnera, ſi placeo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <l>Saepe mihi Babylon patera propinat, &amp; auro,</l>
                  <l>Ingeminatque me is auribus, euge, bibe.</l>
                  <l>Non faciam, vel ſi Coelum miſcebitur Orco,</l>
                  <l>Non faciam, meretrix impia, non faciam.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:9548:11"/>
               <lg n="10">
                  <l>O ſitio tamen, O vocem ſit is intercludit!</l>
                  <l>Nate, cruore ſitim comprime, Lacte Parens.</l>
                  <l>Dic matri, meus hic frater ſitit, optima Mater,</l>
                  <l>Vis de fonte tuo promere, deque meo?</l>
                  <l>Dic Nato, tuus hic frater, mi mellee fili</l>
                  <l>Captiuus monſtrat vincula, lytron habes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <l>Ergo redemptorem monſtra te iure vocari</l>
                  <l>Nobilior reliquis ſi tibi ſanguis in eſt.</l>
                  <l>Tuque Parens monſtra matrem te iure vocari,</l>
                  <l>Vbera ſi reliquis diuitiora geris.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <l>O quando lactabor ab vbere; vulnere paſcar!</l>
                  <l>Delicijſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fruar, Mamma, latuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuis!</l>
                  <l>Parce Deus, magno ſi te clamore fatigem:</l>
                  <l>Non potis Imperio, non potis arte regi.</l>
                  <l>Exagitante ſiti, Patientia perdit habenas,</l>
                  <l>Clamores ſi vis tollere, tolle ſitim.</l>
                  <l>Pluris ego clauis: ſaturaſti ſanguine clauos:</l>
                  <l>Lancea<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> erubuit ſanguine tincta tuo.</l>
                  <l>Pluris ego pannis: maduerunt vndi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> panni</l>
                  <l>Natia vulneribus, Matris ab vberibus.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:9548:9"/>
               <head>TO OVR LADY OF HALL, <hi>AND</hi> TO THE CHILDE IESVS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY thoughts are at a ſtand, of milke &amp; blood</l>
                  <l>(delights of breſt and ſide) which yeelds moſt good.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <l>And ſay when on the teares mine eyes I caſt:</l>
                  <l>O Lady, of thy breſt I beg I a taſt.</l>
                  <l>But if mine eyes vpon the wounds do glide,</l>
                  <l>then (Ieſu) I had rather ſucke thy ſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <l>Long haue I muſed, now know I where to reſt</l>
                  <l>for with my right hand I will graſpe the breſt,</l>
                  <l>(If ſo I may preſume) as for the wounds:</l>
                  <l>with left ile catch them: thus my zeale abounds. <note place="margin">A mixture of Chriſts blood &amp; a creatures milke to make vp the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which which muſt heale our ſoules.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <l>And of the milke, and blood in mixture, make</l>
                  <l>the ſoueraignſt cordiall ſinfull ſoule can take.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <l>Theſe wounds corrupted vlcers mundifies</l>
                  <l>which none can cure vnleſſe he cauterize.</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9548:10"/>
                  <l>Thoſe breſts the fainting <hi>Iſmael</hi> well would cheriſh</l>
                  <l>whom <hi>Sara</hi> ſcorn'd and <hi>Agar</hi> would not nouriſh:</l>
                  <l>The firſt from me expels all peſtilence:</l>
                  <l>the ſecond driues all lingring feauers hence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <l>Doth Ire belch fire, or luſt like Aetna ſmoketh? <note place="margin">How the blood and the milke are made equal</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>either the blood or milke this feruor choketh.</l>
                  <l>Doth enuies ruſt enroule me round about?</l>
                  <l>this milke, or that ſame blood ſoone ſcoures it out.</l>
                  <l>Or do vaine glorious tumor ſtuffe me ſtill</l>
                  <l>her's blood and milke inough my thirſt to fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <l>Mother and Sonne giue eare to what I craue:</l>
                  <l>I begge this milke, that blood, and both would haue</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <l>Yongling, that in thy mothers armes art playing</l>
                  <l>ſucking her breſt ſometimes, and ſometime ſtaying:</l>
                  <l>Why doeſt thou view me with that looke of ſcorne?</l>
                  <l>tis forceleſſe enuy that gainſt thee is borne.</l>
                  <l>Oft haſt thou ſayd (being angry at my ſinne)</l>
                  <l>dareſt thou deſire the teates my foode lies in? <note place="margin">Here the milke is aduanced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the blood.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will not, oh I dare not, golden childe</l>
                  <l>my minde from feare is not ſo farre exilde:</l>
                  <l>But one, euen one poore drop I do implore</l>
                  <l>from thy right hand, or ſide: I aske no more.</l>
                  <l>If neither; from thy left hand let one fall:</l>
                  <l>nay from thy foote, rather then none at all.</l>
                  <l>If I diſpleaſe thee let thy wounds me wound:</l>
                  <l>but pay my wage if I in grace be found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <l>Oft-times doth Babylon in gold me ſend</l>
                  <l>ſtrong wine, and whiſpers to me, drinke my friend.</l>
                  <l>No, no, though heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and hel ſhold make confuſion</l>
                  <l>Ile none falſe ſtrumpet, hence with thine illuſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:9548:11"/>
               <lg n="10">
                  <l>But ah, I thirſt: ah droght my breath doth ſmother</l>
                  <l>quench me with blood ſweet Son, with milke good Mother</l>
                  <l>Say to thy Mother, ſee my brothers thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Mother your milke will eaſe him at the firſt.</l>
                  <l>Say to thy Sonne, Behold thy brothers bands,</l>
                  <l>ſweet Son, thou haſt his ranſome in thy hands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt:</l>
                  <l>thou Sonne, if that thy blood excell the reſt.</l>
                  <l>And ſhew thy ſelfe iuſtly ſo ſtilde indeed,</l>
                  <l>thou Mother, if thy breſts the reſt exceed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <l>Ah when ſhall I with theſe be ſatisfide?</l>
                  <l>when ſhall I ſwim in ioyes of breſt and ſide?</l>
                  <l>Pardon (O God) mine eager earneſtneſſe:</l>
                  <l>if I thy lawes, and reaſons bounds tranſgreſſe.</l>
                  <l>Where thirſt ore ſwayes, patience is thruſt away:</l>
                  <l>ſtay but my thirſt and then my cryes will ſtay,</l>
                  <l>I am better then thy nailes: yet did a ſtreame</l>
                  <l>of thy deere blood waſh both the lance and them.</l>
                  <l>More worthy I then clouts: yet them a flood</l>
                  <l>Moiſtned of Mothers Milke, and of Sons blood.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:12"/>
            <head>THE APPROBA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THIS AVTHOR.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Larus Bonarſcius,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Carolus Scribanius</hi> is a Ieſuit now liuing at Antwerpe, and of much account amongſt them; he wrote this booke, and ſpewed this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy out of his vncleane heart ſome foure or fiue yeeres agoe. And whereas both the Author and his booke deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the fire and halter, it was ſo farre from being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked in the Romiſh Sinagogue, or any way cenſured, that ſince then the booke hath bin reprinted and the Author and his booke ſtand enrolled, approued and commended (in their great volumes ſet out for that purpoſe) for good and Catholike.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glori Bornaſcij Amphitheatrum Honoris Ieſuitici, in quo Caluniſtarum in ſocietatem Ieſu criminationes iugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latae. Proſtant palaeopoli</hi> 1605 <hi>&amp; poſtea</hi> 1606. <hi>Haec Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeuinus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Palaeopoli h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c eſt Antuerpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Apparar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſacro Tom</hi> 1. <hi>l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it. G. pag.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. <hi>edition is vltim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:9548:13"/>
            <p>And it is to be noted that theſe volumes of Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine containe only an inrolement and approbation of no writers at all, ſaue ſuch as are approued Romiſh Catholicks: and are ſet out with great and publike al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of the Romiſh State, as may be ſeene at the beginning of the firſt Tome.</p>
            <p>Beſides, let all men know the booke ſtands yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſured, and the man liues ſtill vnpuniſhed; nay, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reproued, or rather commended and rewarded for it: therefore this cannot be called an obſcure or priuate fact, but may properly be held the fact of the Romiſh Church or State.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:9548:13"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE OF THE LADIES OF HALL AND SI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem, in way of preface ſhewing particularly the <hi>occaſion of this new Goſpell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE bleſſed <hi>Mother of our Lord,</hi> as the Church in all ages hath done, ſo doth ours, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour, as the moſt bleſſed of all Saints, yet as a creature, and as one ſaued by <hi>her ſonne,</hi> that <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in whom her ſpirit reioyced:</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luke 2.</note> we know &amp; acknowledge that not ſhe but the <hi>holy ghoſt</hi> hath ſaid that <hi>all generations ſhall call her</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Luke</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed:</hi> Yet we muſt confeſſe, we are of that fathers religion, who ſaid, <note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt lib. de virginit.</note> 
               <hi>her ſpiritual bearing of Chriſt was happier then her</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9548:14"/> 
               <hi>carnall, and her ſelfe more bleſſed by conceiuing Chriſt in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ellcior par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſpiritualis quam carnalis beatior enim Maria ſuit con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipiend, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ſide qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earne materna enim propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas nihil ei profuiſſet niſi felicius, chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum corde qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earne geſtaſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>her heart then in her wombe, and by beleeuing in him then by bearing him: for her bearing him in her body would not haue ſaued her ſoule, if ſhe had not more happily borne him in her heart.</hi> And in another place, <note n="d" place="margin">Idem Inde felix quia verbum Dei cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtodiuit non quia in illa ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum caro fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt. Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues cannot deny but our men do (out of this caſe) ſpeak and write moſt reuerently of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, as namely, Luther, Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampadius, Bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius, Spangen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergins, vrb. Rhegus, Bucer Bullinger. All this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius the great papiſt in his The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ure Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>helico. To. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Li. 3: at 5. p. 300.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe was happy and bleſſed, not becauſe in her the word was made fleſh, but becauſe ſhe heard the word of God and kept it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This her bleſſedneſſe, far be it from vs to impeach: and who would not yeeld her all bleſſedneſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that a creature may haue, of whom GOD vouchſafed to take the fleſh of <hi>man?</hi> And if any of our Religion hath giuen any words of her, that may giue the leaſt blemiſh to her bleſſed ſtate, it was not done in any the leaſt <hi>contempt</hi> of her, but in the <hi>zeale,</hi> they bare to the honor of their <hi>Sauior,</hi> whom they held diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured by the vnequall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring of her with him: for what will not a Chriſtian mans zeale cauſe him to do, when he ſeeth his God diſhonoured? who would haue thought that <hi>Moſes</hi> would haue caſt ſo careleſly out of his hands, ſo precious a Iewell as were the two Tables written with the finger of God? and yet when he heard the name of the <hi>Lord</hi> blaſphemed, he forgot himſelfe and them, and as though he remembed <hi>none but God,</hi> he threw them away and brake them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Moſes</hi> his zeale makes his haſtines excuſable, then no reaſon to condemne them whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> gaue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to their paſſions, and cauſed them for the honor of the <hi>Creator</hi> to forget the priuiledge of a <hi>Creature:</hi> &amp; I dare ſay there was neuer learned man of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9548:14"/> that preſumed to touch the very skirt of the garment of her glory, vnleſſe they ſaw her ſet in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> which ſeeing the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church dare offer to doe, thereby ecclipſing the glory of <hi>Gods mercie</hi> and the worthyneſſe of <hi>Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> wee hold it our duties to bee zealous for the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonauenture</hi> himſelfe ſaid that we muſt take heed leaſt we ſo farre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſh the glory of the ſonne.</note> glorie of our God, and to preſerue as farre as in vs li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the prerogatiues of our Sauiour. If it be ſaid, that they match her not with God or <hi>Chriſt:</hi> I anſwer they doe, and that in ſuch a meaſure, as wee dare pronounce her or any Angell <hi>accurſed</hi> that ſhould either arrogate or accept of that which the Romiſh religion aſcribes vnto her. Too good euidence hereof hath beene ſeene in all ages for theſe 200. yeares laſt paſt, wherein they haue fallen from honoring her as a <hi>Saint,</hi> to magnifie her as a <hi>Mediator:</hi> to pray to her as to a <hi>God,</hi> to truſt in her as in a <hi>Sauiour:</hi> Many perticulars haue beene ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified by many of <hi>our writers</hi> which by the <hi>aduerſaries</hi> could neuer be <hi>denyed</hi> (they are ſo euident) &amp; yet were they neither <hi>recanted</hi> nor <hi>remooued,</hi> but contrary-wiſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reinoldus de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatria. Catalogus teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um veritatis. Perkins,</hi> of the Idolatry of the laſt times.</note> they haue proceeded from euill to worſe, till their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy haue euen pierced the <hi>heauens</hi> and touched the Crowne of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> and confronted the wounds, merrits and bloud of our <hi>Sauiour.</hi> Perticular inſtances hereof are many, which may be collected out of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of late yeares, part wherof ſhall if God permit be particularized in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>But aboue all there is one, which as it is the lateſt, ſo is it the fowleſt, and wherein Popiſh Blaſpemy is at that height, as now it giues hope to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9548:15"/> men that their prayers are heard, her end is at <note place="margin">Reuel.</note> hand, and that <hi>her iniquity is come vp before God,</hi> and there remaines nothing but the reuenging hand of God to bee ſtretched out vpon her. Wee haue it not from the report of merchants, from the letters of the Poſts, nor from the Intelligence of Embaſſadours, for then our aduerſaries might ſuſpect it: Nor from the report or writings of our owne men, for then let the world not beleeue vs: but wee haue it from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it ſelfe euen from the <hi>Record</hi> wherein it is written with the <hi>Authors</hi> hand: and ſurely if the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence were not beyond exception, our ſelues would not beleeue it of them, though they bee our enemies. Thus ſtandeth the caſe.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the late deuices that Romiſh pollicy hath forged to vphold their Hierarchy, a principall is, their <hi>art of Miracles,</hi> which they pretend to haue ſo ordinary, that in many Churches they haue more <note place="margin">In So yeeres the Pope loſt all England, Scotland, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Denmark Sweden, and a great part of Germany, France, Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</note> 
               <hi>miracles</hi> then <hi>ſermons:</hi> but alas dayly experience ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that they be <hi>lying Wonders</hi> and no true miracles. Now becauſe ſuch tricks are moſt effectuall to delude the common people, and that they finde themſelues and their cauſe to haue loſt much of late in many parts of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">a</hi> therefore to recouer themſelues and to gaine credit to their forlorne cauſe, they haue moſt buſily applyed this point of late, and haue by the craft of Machiauilian <hi>Ieſuits</hi> (as <hi>Watſon</hi> their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">In their quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libets often.</note> Prieſt often ſtiles them) ſo farre preuayled, that there ſcarce paſſeth a month wherin ſome new Image of our Lady is not found, or ſome ſtrange miracle and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9548:15"/> wonders heard of.</p>
            <p>Two yeares agoe they cauſed a ſtory to bee written and publiſhed wherein they bluſh not to make their <note place="margin">See the booke called, <hi>Iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij diua. Virgo. Hallenſis.</hi>
               </note> people beleeue, that more miracles, and greater then Chriſt did, haue beene and are dayly done at <hi>Hall</hi> (a towne on the borders of <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Henault)</hi> by the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> at a Picture of hers in a Chappell there: and this is ſet out by no triuiall or vulgar fellow, but by that famous Apoſtata <hi>Lipſius,</hi> that the tale may carry the more credit: and the miracles are not of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary but of the higheſt nature: for healing of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſies, feuers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uultions, is nothing, nay: ſight is giuen to the <note place="margin">Iai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> daughter</note> blind, and whereas Chriſt raiſed but 3. from the dead (that we know of) our Lady of <hi>Hall</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lipſius)</hi> gaue life to 7. at leaſt that were dead: Loe here how far ſhort Chriſt himſelfe is of his Mother: and now we maruaile <note place="margin">Omniae quae fecit Chriſtus fecit Franciſcus plura quam fecit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus fecit Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum beati Franciſci.</note> no more if they haue written that <hi>St. Francis did all that Chriſt did, and more then Chriſt did,</hi> ſeeing the Picture of his Mother, can do more then he did.</p>
            <p>I ſay the Picture of his Mother, becauſe <hi>Georgius fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> the Popes cenſor of books, in his allowance of this Legend of <hi>Lipſius</hi> ſaith, that God giueth and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicateth diuine power to worke miracles nor onely to the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> and the <hi>Saints,</hi> but euen to their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages or Pictures: behold good reader a worthy piece of new refined Popery, <hi>Gods diuine power is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Strange doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Popery</note> 
               <hi>communicated to the very pictures of creatures:</hi> And if any man obiect that miracles are not in theſe dayes to bee expected, <hi>Lipſius</hi> hath a learned and Catholike anſwer,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9548:16"/> that now indeed in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or to auerre his Doctrine, or to maintaine his honour, they neede not, but the eaſe is otherwiſe (ſaith he) with the <hi>Saints,</hi> for many do refuſe to worſhip them, and grudge at the honour that in the Romiſh Church is giuen them, and therefore to defend them in this point, and to eſtabliſh <note place="margin">By Popiſh doctrine chriſt doth more to eſtabliſh the worſhipping of Saints then his owne.</note> that worſhip which they do vnto them, God ſuffereth ſo many miracles to bee done euen by their <hi>Images:</hi> which anſwere being well conſidred of, what a kind of Doctrine it contayneth, I leaue to the learned and iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reader.</p>
            <p>I only ſay, that if this be true, then how forteth it with the very body and current of his ſtory, by which no man can deny, but it is apparant that moſt of the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which he ſpecifieth, were done almoſt 200. yeares a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe, namely betwixt the yeares 1400. and 1500. long before <hi>Luther</hi> began to preach, and (as they ſay) afore our Religion was in the world, and conſequently before the worſhipping of Saints was withſtood; therefore it followeth, that miracles were ordained at Saints Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, euen then when worſhipping of Saints was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied: <hi>Lipſius</hi> might haue done well to haue reconciled ſo euident a contradiction.</p>
            <p>But what aſſurance haue we for the truth of theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles? or how know we that this is an approoued Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our Lady? <hi>Lipſius</hi> anſwereth that there was one <hi>Sophia</hi> daughter to the <hi>Landgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> by his Lady Saint <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> (a Saint of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. making within foure yeeres after her death.)</p>
            <p>This <hi>Sophia</hi> (ſaith he) as it is thought, had certaine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9548:16"/> of our Lady, giuen her by her Mother <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (was it then but thought ſo, and muſt wee now beleeue it?) one of theſe ſhe gaue to the Nunnes of the Nunry at Vilvord, and that was called <hi>our Lady of comfort:</hi> 2. more ſhe gaue to <hi>Madam Machtild,</hi> or <hi>Maud,</hi> her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſiſter, who beſtowed them thus: one ſhe gaue to <hi>Graueſand,</hi> another to <hi>Harlem</hi> (two townes in <hi>Holland)</hi> the third (which it ſeemes ſtole all the vertue from both the other) to <hi>Hall</hi> a towne in <hi>Henalt,</hi> (and this is that we now ſpeake of:) and to ad more credit to the ſtory, he tels vs that this Lady <hi>Maude</hi> was Mother to that Lady <hi>Mawde,</hi> who bare at one birth 364. chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <note place="margin">An old ſtory, but greatly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> and other learned men, to be fabulous</note> which were all borne aliue, and baptized by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: So (ſaith <hi>Lipſius)</hi> this is that Image, which now wee worſhip at <hi>Hall:</hi> and thus ſtrong a foundation hath the Story: and now may not all <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to doubt of this Story or to ſuſpect theſe grounds?</p>
            <p>Now therefore ſurely we muſt needes beleeue (els we are vnbeleeuing Hereticks) that one was before this Image diſpoſſeſſed of a Diuell without any other meanes, for ſo he ſaith, &amp; that ten at leaſt were deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from preſent death by but calling or thinking vpon <hi>our Lady at Hall,</hi> and that ſeuen were raiſed from death to life being but laid before the Image; and all theſe within the ſpace of 20. yeares, and in one country (ſo ordinary a matter it is in Popery to raiſe the dead.) Nay wee muſt beleeue (or elſe wee are Infidels) that when a Faulkner ſhould haue beene hanged for looſing his Lords Faulkon, and had the rope about his neck, <note place="margin">An excellent &amp; new found way for faulkners to find their loſt Hawkes, neuer before heard of Proue this <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> and thou wilt haue many Faulkners turn Papiſts.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9548:17"/> and did but call to mind the <hi>Lady of Hall,</hi> forthwith the Hawke came flying home againe, and lighted vpon the Faulconers ſhoulder, and ſo ſaued his life: for this is not <hi>Lipſius</hi> aſhamed to report. Which if it be true, then we ſhall leſſe wonder heereafter at that in the <hi>Legend,</hi> where it is reported how a Parrat hauing got abroad out of her Cage, and ſporting her ſelfe in the aire, was by and by eſpyed by a Hawke, who being ready to <note place="margin">See the old Engliſh legend in folio, of the life of <hi>S.</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</note> ſeaze vpon her, inſtantly the Parrat ſeeing her ſelfe in danger to be ſurprized, cryed out <hi>S. Thomas a Becket</hi> ſaue me, and preſently the Hawke fell downe dead, and the Parrat was deliuered.</p>
            <p>As alſo thoſe miracles of <hi>S. Francis</hi> ſo far beyond <hi>Chriſts</hi> or his Apoſtles, that he tamed wild beaſts, that <note place="margin">See the booke called, <hi>liber con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitatum, S. Franciſci,</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impreſſion.</note> he preacht vnto a <hi>Wolfe,</hi> and conuerted him from his cruelty, and calling him by the name of his brother <hi>Wolfe,</hi> made the towne of <hi>Engubium</hi> &amp; him friends, who of long time had beene at contention, and for the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the peace, he made his brother <hi>Wolfe</hi> to giue him his faith in the Market place, before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and afterward the <hi>Wolfe</hi> went vp and downe the City, and tooke his meate from dore to dore. Loe here you Heretikes, here is a Miracle worth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and if they will not beleeue me, looke in the holy Booke of Conformities, and there you ſhall find all <note place="margin">See the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the old impreſſion and his life in Engliſh.</note> this and much more: as namely, how the Birds would come flying, and the Beaſts flocking about him to heare him preach, and how the Nightingales and other Birds would come and helpe him to ſay Maſſe, and ſing his office, and would anſwere him Verſe for Verſe.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9548:17"/> Come out ye Heretikes <hi>(Caluiniſts</hi> and <hi>Lutherans)</hi> Saint <hi>Francis</hi> and his followers challenge you all to bring <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sedulius</hi> a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh writer hath this laſt yeare defended all theſe.</note> out one miracle like theſe, to approue your Religion: ſurely they may, and for ought I ſee <hi>Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> alſo, for they neuer wrought ſuch a Miracle to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the Goſpell. Is it not then apparant that S. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> hath done more then Chriſt did?</p>
            <p>Oh my deare country-men (you that name your ſelues the Catholikes of England) if you would but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your eyes and conſider of this, I durſt make your ſelues Iudges, what diuinity this is: if you ſuſpect mee, beleeue me not, looke into the bookes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and beleeue your owne eyes: If you ſay vnto me that ſome ſuch impieties and follies might creepe into the old Bookes, 100. or 200. yeares agoe when the times were not ſo wary nor ſuſpicious; but the Church hath ſince reformed ſuch abuſes, I anſwere, I alledge moſt of this out of the Booke of confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, lately corrected and printed in Italy within theſe 20. yeares: but if you looke into the old one, printed 100. yeares agoe, (wherewith your forefathers were abuſed) you ſhall there find ſuch matter, as for reuerence of the Reader <hi>I ſhame,</hi> and for the honour of <hi>God</hi> I <hi>feare</hi> to write.</p>
            <p>And as for theſe miracles at our Ladies Picture at <hi>Hall</hi> they were neuer offred to the worlds view nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came to light till within theſe 3. yeares that <hi>Lipſius</hi> (a man who durſt doe any thing but honour Chriſt) preſumed to publiſh them, and with foule impiety to write that in theſe dayes <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his doctrine, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9548:18"/> and Religion needes no miracles but the Saints and their ſeruice and worſhip do ſtand in neede there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and as in the infancy of the Church <hi>Chriſt</hi> had his, ſo in the perfect ſtate of it, <hi>Saints</hi> and their Images muſt haue their miracles: but obſerue withall that (if <note place="margin">See the confor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mity of the old impreſſion, or his life in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> they ſay true) more ſtrange and as I may ſo ſay, more <hi>Miraculous Miracles</hi> are done by the honour of <hi>Saints,</hi> and approouing the worſhipping of them and their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, then were for the eſtabliſhing of the Goſpell, the abrogating of the Ceremoniall Law, and for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be the Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Lipſius</hi> were liuing I would not ſpare to tell him: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lipſius</hi> dyed a relapſed papiſt at <hi>Louoin.</hi> Ano</note> that this his Doctrine ſmels ſtrongly of that whereof he hath beene, (it ſeemes not without cauſe) ſuſpected, which becauſe he is dead I will forbeare to name.</p>
            <p>But ſome of our Engliſh Papiſts (which are not learned) may doubt whether there bee ſuch a Booke or no, or if it be not deuiſed by vs, and fathered on them, (for ſo do their Prieſts often ſuggeſt vnto them of ſuch Bookes as they feare the people will miſlike) but if any of their miſleaders doe ſo miſ-informe them, let them know the Booke hath beene twice printed at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and once at <hi>Paris,</hi> with allowance of authority in both places, not onely of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Books, and the Archbiſhop of the place, but the matter and miracles in the Booke are confirmed <note place="margin">Theſe bulls of 2. Popes are in the end of the booke.</note> with the Bulls of a Popes, one of Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> in the yeare 1451. the other of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. within theſe 8. yeares: and if any ſhould bee ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reeſonable as to thinke that wee haue forged all this,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9548:18"/> 
               <hi>Poſſeuine, the Ieſuite</hi> may giue him full ſatisfaction: who in his <hi>Apparatus ſacer</hi> hath publiſhed to the world that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Lipſius vir vere Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus inter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plures eruditis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimos l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> anno</hi> 604. <hi>edidit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne. Iuſti Liptij diua vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſque beneficia &amp; miracula bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na fide atque or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine deſcripta. Antuerpia apud moret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Poſſe. Appa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa. To.</hi> 2. <hi>in litera. I page</hi> 318. <hi>Iuſti Lipſij diua Aſpric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lipſius</hi> in the yeare and at the place aforenamed, did put out ſuch a worke, and giues him ſpeciall commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for his labours, in that and the like for the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſe.</p>
            <p>But hath not <hi>Lipſius</hi> recanted, or the Romiſh Church reformed this ſince then? Alas, <hi>Lipſius</hi> was ſo farre from that, that the yeare after, very neere vnto his death, as though he intended nothing but <hi>to heape vp wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of wrath,</hi> he added <hi>drunkenneſſe to thirſt,</hi> as the Prophet ſaith, for heaping ſin vpon ſin, inſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking &amp; recanting his former colluſion, he publiſhed another pamphlet, a more ridiculous Legend, and fraught with more improbabilities and impoſſibilities then the former. It beares this Title: <hi>Iuſtus Lipſius his Hiſtory of our Lady of Sichem, or of our Ladies Picture of the craggy-rocke or ſharpe hill, and of her new miracles and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits: at Antwerpe.</hi> 1605.</p>
            <p>At this Image ſaith he, are wrought miracles of al ſorts Apoplexis, Epilepſies, gouts and all kind of diſeaſes are healed, lame are reſtored to limbes, blinde to ſight, deafe to their hearing: and all by theſe heapes, not ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or extraordinarily, but yearely monthly, dayly: almoſt 60. are regiſtred by <hi>Lipſius</hi> beſides many more omitted, and all to be done in 2. or 3. yeares, inſomuch as if his report be true, God makes miracles farre more ordinary for the honour of Saints and their Images, then he did for confirming the doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: But what credit hath the Story of our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9548:19"/> Lady of <hi>Sichem?</hi> euen as good as hath our Lady of <hi>Hall,</hi> elſe let the Reader iudge. <note place="margin">The tale of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>age of craggy Hill,</note>
            </p>
            <p>Neere to the little poore (but old) towne of <hi>Sichem</hi> ſaith <hi>Lipſius,</hi> there is a mount, barren, rough, and craggy, on oue ſide thereof there is a little Hillocke: on it growes an Oake, and in it or faſtned to it, is a little I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of our Lady, which hath done great miracles in time paſt, and was therefore worſhipped of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there: but how is that proued? thus; about 100 yeares agoe, a <hi>Shepheard</hi> found that Image, and put it in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, thinking to carry it home to worſhip it, but as he was in theſe thoughts, he was ſodainely ſtrucken and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſht in his ſences, &amp; benummed in his whole body, inſomuch as he could not ſtirre one foote but ſtood ſtil like a dead trunke, not knowing what to thinke of it, nor how to helpe himſelfe: his M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. wanting both his ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard and his ſheepe, ſought them, and found him ſo ſtanding, who told him the whole matter: his M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Image, went with great deuotion and ſet it vp in the Oake againe, and forthwith the ſhepheard had his limbs reſtored, &amp; went &amp; worſhipped it, and ſo by their reports, all the country heard of it, who came by heaps &amp; were healed of all diſeaſes, but agues eſpecially: and ſo it continued (ſaith he) til within theſe 20. yeares, about which time the bleſſed Image was ſtolne or loſt no man can tell how. (But is it not ſtrange that if it could doe theſe Miracles, they would let it be loſt ſo careleſly?) well, loſt it was: But what tho? people went as faſt then as afore, and ſtill as great cures were there done as when the Image was there: and in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9548:19"/> want of the Image, the people worſhipped the Oake, &amp; why might they not ſay <hi>Lipſius,</hi> the holy Image had hallowed the Tree? ſo that it might lawfully bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: (be hold Popiſh deuotion!) yet, ſaith he, wee worſhipped not the Tree, but in it the Image, and in it our Lady &amp; in her God. <hi>Marke good Reader, God gets his worſhip at laſt, though it be at the fourth hand:</hi> they tender it to the tree, the tree yeelds it to the Image, the Image conueyes to our Lady, and ſhe preſents it to God: ſo then by Popiſh doctrine and deuotion God is ſerued and honoured after his creatures, and ſo at laſt gets his own. If they ſay that the worſhip is intended to God, &amp; is not ended but in him: I anſwere; but were it not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the worſhip were offred immediately from the heart and hands of the worſhipper to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to paſſe through no hands, but of his Sonne the Mediator? <hi>but this is Hereſie let it paſſe, or elſe it muſt paſſe the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To returne to the ſtory: our Lady of <hi>Sichem</hi> is loſt; but what then muſt the poore towne looſe her traffick and liuing? <hi>(Nay rather wee will make another, for that is no hard nor vnlawfull thing in that Religion:)</hi> and ſo ſaith he 7. yeares after: an honeſt and deuout Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Sichem (perceiuing well how his and his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures gaines came in, and how the poore towne liued)</hi> like a good towneſman, made another Image, put it in a boxe of wood, and faſtened the Boxe to the Oake that ſo their Lady might not bee loſt ſo careleſly as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>This new Image thus made, did as many miracles
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9548:20"/> as the other, <hi>and why ſhould it not for was it not as good as the other? nay it may be it was more curiouſly carued and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that I meane not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe ſyee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the bleſſed virgin whom as I hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a bleſſed Saint in heauen, ſo I preſent her with all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that may be giuen to a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature: But I meane Lipſius his Lady of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem, or our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Hall.</note> 
               <hi>better wrought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it continued certaine yeares till at laſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Prieſt perceiuing they began to be well cuſtomed, beſtowed ſome coſt on their Lady which got them ſo much, that they built her a little Chappell of boords, &amp; there placed her. But ſtill their cuſtome growing grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they ſhewed themſelues thankefull to their patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; as ſhe fild their purſes they ſought her honour and built her a faire chappell of ſtone, ſome 2. yeeres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, and in that reſteth the Image, working miracles e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day. <hi>But what become of the holy Oake?</hi> it was cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by pieces by deuout perſons, and carried away, that it was in danger of falling, and a counſell was called in the towne what were to be done with it <hi>(as in ſo great a matter it is requiſite)</hi> and there, after ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, it was grauely concluded, that it ſhould bee cut vp by the rootes, &amp; with much ſolemnity brought into the towne of Sichem, where when it came, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with happy was he that could get a piece of the holy Wood, whereof (ſaith <hi>Lipſius,</hi> and bluſheth not to write it) diuers made them little Images, and with much piety do worſhip them: others that were ſicke of grieueous dieaſes, ſhaued it into their drinke and drunke, and ſo were healed. <hi>See what an excellent Religion this is:</hi> one Image hath begot many, and the firſt Image being but faſtned to the Tree, ſo ſanctified the whole Oake, that euery Image made of the whole Tree, ſhould be as good as it ſelfe, and euery crumme
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9548:20"/> of the Wood ſhould worke Miracles as faſt as the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage did.</p>
            <p>Loe here the Hiſtory of our Lady of <hi>Sichem,</hi> or of the ſharp hill: &amp; this legend is not <hi>Lipſius</hi> aſhamed to thruſt vpon the world, for a true &amp; vndoubted ſtory: ſuch are the times we be fallen into, that to ſet faſt the crowne vpon the Popes head, truth muſt ſtand aſide, and lyes muſt paſſe for currant without controule: and ſuch a cauſe is Popery as cannot continue in credit before the people, but by forging a continuall ſucceſſion of lying wonders, for now we are made beleeue, that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> hath 2. Images within few miles together which haue done more miracles in a few yeares by-paſt, then God himſelfe did in the old, or Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the new Teſtament: Such Idols of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation doth the Romiſh harlot aduance againſt the ſoueraigne maieſty of God, to prouoke him withall: for what is it but an Idoll of indignation, that not a creature only, but the very Image of a creature ſhould be made pertaker of the diuine power and Maieſty of God?</p>
            <p>The time was when <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet durſt ſay of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 42. 28,</note> God, <hi>I am the Lord, this is my name, and my glory I will not giue vnto another, nor my praiſe to grauen Images:</hi> but how ſoeuer that might be tollerable doctrine in thoſe dayes had he liued in theſe, he muſt haue beene taught that a part of the glory and praiſe of God, may dayly be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to grauen Images, and yet the glory of God not at all thereby impeached, but rather augmented: Loe what Idols of indignations and abhominations lye hid
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9548:21"/> vnder the miſtery of iniquity.</p>
            <p>And yet good Reader (as God ſaith vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>(turne thee a little</hi> and <hi>thou ſhalt ſee greater abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezeth.</note> 
               <hi>then theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is yet ſcarce 3. yeares agoe ſince the tale of our Lady of <hi>Hall,</hi> was forged by ſome Ieſuit, and publiſhed by <hi>Lipſius,</hi> when withall a faire Picture grauen in braſſe was prefixed vpon the firſt Page before the booke of <hi>our Lady holding her Sonne in her armes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And behold, the Ieſuits as though the Mother were a woman, and the Sonne but an Infant: or as though they had gained enough by Chriſt a ready, and would now ſee what they could get by the Mother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to call in queſtion his <hi>merits</hi> and mediation, and the dignity of his <hi>wounds</hi> and ſuffrings, and at laſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that his <hi>wounds</hi> and her <hi>paps</hi> his <hi>bloud</hi> and her milke, are either all one, or elſe that the <hi>milke is better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet before we enter into the particular, let the Reader obſerue that though the Image be both of our Lady (as they call her) and of her Sonne Ieſus our Lord, yet notwithſtanding the miracles are all aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>to her</hi> and her Picture, and none to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> for the colouring of which impiety, what they can ſay I ſee not, vnleſſe they dare affirme that the ſonne will doe no miracles in the preſence of his Mother, to which end, it may well be noted, and generally in all places where the Mother and the ſonne, the Virgin Mary, and our <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> be pictured together in their Churches, ſhee is alwayes ſet forth as a woman and a Mother, and hee as a Child and Infant, either in her
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9548:21"/> armes or in her hand, that ſo the common people might haue occaſion to imagine, that looke what power of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerruling and commanding the <hi>Mother</hi> hath ouer her <hi>little child,</hi> the ſame hath <hi>ſhe</hi> ouer her ſon Ieſus: and that ſeeing the ſonne is but an infant in his mothers armes, therefore they might not wonder why her picture doth all the miracles, and his none; for its like, Chriſt did no miracles whilſt he was a child: into theſe ſuperſtious and euen blaſphemous concelts do they indeauour to driue their people, not caring what they derogate from Chriſt, ſo they giue it to their Saints.</p>
            <p>Is it not admirable that ſtill they will make him an Infant, ſtill in his mothers armes, ſtill vnder her pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſtill all miracles muſt be wrought by her, and at her picture, as though either he could not, or in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſence would not, or (at the leaſt) as though ſhe had many enemies, and therefore needed miracles, and Chriſt none?</p>
            <p>But alas who ſeeth not that the Athiſme &amp; prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the world cauſeth euen the name and religion of Chriſt to be blaſphemed, that if miracles might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be expected, wee ſhould thinke them as needefull as euer ſince the firſt planting of the Goſpell: it is therefore a ſtrange piece of Popiſh doctrine, that there is more cauſe that the Virgin Mary, and her Picture ſhould haue miracles for them, then Chriſt and his Religion.</p>
            <p>But yet this, and all other their ſuſpitious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious ſpeeches and practiſes againſt the honour of Chriſt &amp; his Religion, are in my iudgement inferiour,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9548:22"/> and may all ſtoupe to this new impiety of the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> whereby the <hi>Mother</hi> is compared to the <hi>Sonne,</hi> not as being a child, or a man, but as the Sauiour and media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: &amp; the pappes of a <hi>Woman</hi> equalled with the <hi>wounds</hi> of our <hi>Lord,</hi> and her <hi>milke</hi> with his <hi>bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this were written by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſome might ſay we might report partially, or if it were a matter of old, the age might yeeld ſuſpition that it were made worſe in the carriage: But when it is a matter of yeſterday and comes from themſelues, partiallity it ſelfe cannot cauill againſt it.</p>
            <p>And the particular is this, <hi>Clarus Bonarſcius,</hi> a Ieſuit or the Ieſuits Patron, publiſhed this preſent yeare to the world, a volume large enough, in defence of the whole order of Ieſuits, the booke beares this title.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Clari Bonarſcij Amphitheatrum Honoris.</hi> In quo <hi>Caluiniſtarum in ſocietatem Ieſu, criminationes Iugulatae.</hi> Editio altera, libro quarto auctior. <hi>Palaeopoli Aduaticorum, apud</hi> Alexandrum Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heidon 1606.</q>
            <p>This volume he erected, as a Theater, yea an <hi>Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theater of Honour,</hi> in defence of the Ieſuits wherein af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had aſſaied with much ſleight of wit, and in a ſtrange ſtile, to wipe away many foule blots, with which that Atheiſticall broode hath ſtained the <hi>holy name of Ieſus,</hi> and adorned it ſelfe (for generally that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9548:22"/> which diſhonors God adornes them) and after he had ranged ouer all the former Churches, and raked vp all rotten ſlaunders, and reuiued the callumniations that were anſwered, dead and buried, 40. 50. and 60. yeares agoe, and rayled vpon the liuing and dead, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Beza, Pareus, Stenius, Toſſanus, Faius,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy and learned men, with that bitterneſſe and virulency as neuer was before him: yea, moreouer after that hee had laid high and horrible imputations vpon this whole ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> and (like a true Ieſuits Impe) ſlandred the whole gouernment, with foule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, and monſtrous cruelty in many perticulars, and <note place="margin">See for theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of our Queen &amp; ſtate lib.</note> had in Ieſuiticall pride, dared to defile the name and honour of renowned Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory for euer will bee bleſſed) with words vnworthy the mouth of man (if hee were not a Ieſuite) at laſt from the defence of Ieſuits, hee falls to defend <hi>Lypſius,</hi> (a good friend of theirs) and his two ſtories of our Lady of <hi>Hall,</hi> and our <hi>Lady of the craggie Rock,</hi> and not only labours to to make good all his fancies and fables, but further (to ſhew that a Ieſuit hath one trick of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety beyond all, and is anointed by the Diuell with the oyle of miſchiefe aboue all his fellowes) addeth a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of verſes directed to that Picture, which he calleth <hi>our Lady of Hall,</hi> fraught with ſo many blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>merits</hi> of the <hi>Mediator,</hi> as no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian eares to this day did euer heare, and doubtleſſe no Chriſtian heart can patiently endure: and certainely if the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to whoſe picture he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated them, may be his Iudge, without doubt both
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9548:23"/> hee and his blaſphemy will bee condemned to hell: and ſhe <hi>whoſe ſoule reioyced in God her Sonne and Sauior,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 47.</note> her ſoule I ſay will reioyce in the iuſt damnation of him who ſhall match the milk of her a <hi>creature,</hi> with the bloud of him her <hi>Sauiour:</hi> But ſhall we heare them? no will ſome ſay, let blaſphemy rather bee buried in the depth of obliuion, darken not the <hi>Sunne,</hi> defile not the <hi>heauens,</hi> poyſon not the <hi>ayre,</hi> burden not the earth with it, amaze not the <hi>minds,</hi> and terrifie not the <hi>conſciences</hi> of weake Chriſtians: and aſſuredly could I <hi>bury</hi> it ſo that it might neuer <hi>liue,</hi> and <hi>quench</hi> it ſo as it might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>flame</hi> againe, and if my Booke were the onely Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie in the world, I would rather chooſe to couer this ſhame of the ſhameleſſe <hi>whore of Babilon,</hi> then by diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering it to cauſe good mens <hi>eares</hi> to tingle, and their hearts to tremble: But ſeeing the ſtrumpet hath the whores forhead, and glorieth in her owne ſhame, and ſounded out this blaſphemy (as with a trumpet) in the eares of all Chriſtendome by publiſhing it in a booke which he calls <hi>the great theater of the Ieſuits honour,</hi> euen bringing ſo fearefull blaſphemy vpon the ſtage, &amp; dare diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lge it in a ſecond impreſſion, leaſt the world ſhould want it:</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore craue leaue of our <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer her ſhame wherein ſhee glorieth, and that wee may without impeachment of his honour, repeate ſo foule blaſphemy, that ſo the world may both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what a Religion Popery is, and that we for our parts <hi>haue no fellowſhip with ſuch abhominable workes of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>darkeneſſe</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:9548:23"/>
            <p>The Title he giues them is this:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ad diuam Hallenſem. &amp; Puerum Ieſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is,</p>
               <p>To our Lady of Hall, and The Child Ieſus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>See firſt the impiety lurking in this Title. She is a <hi>Queene</hi> or Lady, Ieſus a <hi>Child</hi> or Infant: compare this with holy Scriptures, they indeede ſpeake both of him and her, but of him as God and a Sauiour, of her as a creature; the Mother only of his humanity (although the Mother of him that was God) and exerciſing pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er onely ouer his humanity, and that onely during his infancy and priuateneſſe, but not after hee tooke vpon him the Propheticall Office of the Mediator, for then he ſaid (in a certaine caſe) <hi>woman, what haue I to do with thee?</hi> and againe, being told<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>ſhee was without to ſpeake</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>with him,</hi> hee anſwered that hee had more Mothers, tho not in the ſame, yet in a better ſence: for <hi>whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did the will of his father, the ſame ſaith he is my mother:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 12. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> thus the ſcripture proceedes to deſcribe him in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall, and afterward in his Prieſtly Office, and leaues him not till at laſt hee be aſcended into heauen, and haue taken poſſeſſion of his kingdome, and then the Scripture leaues him in his glory.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:9548:24"/>
            <p>Is all this true? and yet muſt he now after 1606 years be an Infant in his Mothers armes? And for her the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures ſpeake no more of her, but as of a creature, a woman, a beleeuing Iewe, a holy Saint, ſaued by faith in her ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo leaues her, with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mention (after Chriſt was baptized, and entred his propheticall Office) her <hi>body</hi> to goe the way of all fleſh, and her ſoule to enter into that great glory which Chriſt had purchaſed for her, and all that ſpirituall kindred of his, whom with his owne mouth hee had pronounced <hi>more bleſſed</hi> for <hi>hearing his word &amp; keeping it,</hi> then they could haue beene by being the mother of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</note> his fleſh.</p>
            <p>And yet now after 1600. yeeres, ſhe muſt ſtill bee a commanding Mother, and muſt ſhew <hi>her authority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him,</hi> and he <hi>muſt receiue our prayers by her meanes,</hi> and <note place="margin">Monſtra te eſſe Matrem ſumat per te preces. So are the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, Breuiaries, &amp; Offices that are reformed.</note> ſtill ſhe muſt beare him in her armes, or lead him in her hand, and her Picture muſt worke all the miracles, but his none: and ſhe muſt be ſalured as a Lady, a Queene, a Goddeſſe, and he as a Child: If this be not ſo, let this Title iudge: <hi>Ad Diuam Hallenſem, &amp; puerum Ieſum.</hi> But let vs leaue the Title, and not ſtand long at the <hi>gates,</hi> but enter this <hi>Citty</hi> of confuſion.</p>
            <p>And now all good Chriſtians hearken with griefe of heart to that which I rather wiſh you might neuer haue heard; but if your eares tingle, your haire ſtand vp, and your hearts tremble at the blaſphemy follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, blame the heart that indighted it, the hand that wrote it, the Religion that allowes it, and not the pen that diſcouers it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9548:24"/>
            <head>THVS THEN BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GINS THE IESVITS <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <l>Haereo lac inter meditans interque cruorem,</l>
               <l>Inter delicias <hi>Vberis</hi> &amp; <hi>Lateris.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>My thoughts are at a ſtand of</hi> Milke <hi>and</hi> bloud:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delights of breſt and ſide, which yeelds moſt good.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earken thou bleſſed Apoſtle</hi> Paul, (if thou in heauen canſt heare the blaſphemy on earth) thou that didſt preach and <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2</note> write, that <hi>thou deſiredſt to know nothing but Ieſus Chriſt, and him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied:</hi> thou that didſt teach the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches onely to know and beleeue in <hi>Chriſt</hi> for ſaluation: and almoſt 20. times in thy <hi>Epiſtles</hi> haſt magnified his <hi>Bloud,</hi> without once mentioning the <hi>Virgin</hi> or her <hi>Milke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare and be aſtoniſht at this, that ſome who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9548:25"/> to be thy Diſciples or thy fellowes rather, cannot tell whether to chooſe that <hi>bloud</hi> of the Mediatour, or the <hi>milke</hi> of a woman: At leaſt harken thou <hi>bleſſed ſpirit</hi> of truth, thou that canſt and wilt heare, thou that didſt inſpire thoſe holy truths into that holy <hi>Apoſtle:</hi> behold a Religion riſen vp in the world that dare compare the <hi>bloud of that God</hi> who was by thee conceiued, with the <hi>milke of that W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man,</hi> who was the Mother of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and was ſaued from hell and damnation by that bloud, and that dare allow her profeſſors to make doubt whether to eſteeme the greater delight of their ſoules <hi>her milke</hi> or <hi>his bloud:</hi> and we for repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this, muſt bee accounted Heretikes: heare from heauen we beſeech thee and Iudge betwixt vs.</p>
            <p>The blaſphemer proceedeth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et dico ſi forte oculos ad</hi> Vbera <hi>tendo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diua Parens.</hi> Mammae <hi>gaudia poſco tuae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed dico ſi deinde oculos ad</hi> Vulnera <hi>verto</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Ieſu</hi> Lateris <hi>gaudia malo tuae.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <q>
               <l>And ſay aloud when I the <hi>Teates</hi> do ſee,</l>
               <l>O Goddeſſe mother, lend thy <hi>Breſts</hi> to me!</l>
               <l>But thus I beg, when on the <hi>wounds</hi> I thinke</l>
               <l>O Ieſu giue me from thy <hi>ſide</hi> to drinke.</l>
            </q>
            <p>What before hee deliuered more darkely, now hee maketh plainer: if any doubt what milke what bloud
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9548:25"/> he meant, he anſwereth our Ladyes <hi>Milke,</hi> and <hi>Ieſus Chriſt his bloud:</hi> but what, doth popery make queſtion whether of theſe two is better? Is this their holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Romaine faith? If no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, let their words be Iudge, I ſtand muſing ſaith he and cannot tell whether to take milke or bloud: <hi>If I looke at her paps, then I long for milke, If to his ſides, then I would haue bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Marke how indifferent a Papiſt is, whether he receiue the one or the other: is not this euill enough? a man would thinke ſo, yet hearken what followeth, and wee ſhall heare worſe: but let vs do it with feare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of that glorious name, and precious bloud which are blaſphemed.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rem ſcio, prenſabo ſi fas erit</hi> vbera <hi>dextra</hi> 
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laena prenſabo</hi> vulnera <hi>ſi dabitur.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>In Engliſh thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Long haue I mus'd, now know I where to reſt,</l>
               <l>for with my right hand I will graſpe the breſt:</l>
               <l>(If ſo I may preſume) as for the wounds,</l>
               <l>with left I catch them, thus my zeale abounds.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hetherto he doubted, now he is reſolued: but ſuch a doubt, and ſuch a reſolution, Chriſtian eares neuer heard of: he doubted whether were bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, the <hi>bloud</hi> of God, or the <hi>Milke</hi> of a creature (the diuell himſelfe neuer doubted hereof) but now what is his reſolution, doth it make amends? yes doubtleſſe as the Pope vſeth to make <hi>Chriſt</hi> amends, when he hath diſhonored him:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9548:26"/> I was at a ſtand (ſaith he) whether to take, and now I reſolue I will haue both: both are ſo good I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe neither, her <hi>milke</hi> his <hi>bloud</hi> both ſo precious, both ſo powerfull, both ſo vertuous, as I will haue both. Both are good, and ſo good as hardly can I finde diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence but if there be any, it is that the <hi>Milke</hi> is more excellent, and therefore with my <hi>right hand,</hi> I will make it ſure mine, if I may bee ſo bold as to touch it, or if it be lawfull for a ſinners ſoule to taſte ſo glorious, ſo vnualuable and diuine a liquor as is the <hi>Milke</hi> of the <hi>Mother:</hi> and as for the <hi>child</hi> it is well for him if hee may follow his <hi>Mother,</hi> and haue the next place to her: therefore if hee pleaſe to giue me leaue I will lay hold with my left hand on his wounds.</p>
            <p>O glorious God, the eternall ſonne of the eternall Father, thou bleſſed Ieſus <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſtay and comfort of all Chriſtian ſoules, heare in heauen thine only habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this hainous blaſphemy, and iudge thy own cauſe: And if it fall out that any contagion of ſinne catch hold on me the writer or any the readers here of, by not trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling or not ſufficiently deteſting ſuch feareful impiety as this that is paſt, or that that is to come; vouchſafe in mercy to forgiue it, and to waſh it away with that moſt precious bloud of thine, whereto all the creatures in the world are not worthy to be compared.</p>
            <p>And though this that's paſt, be abhominable, yet with reuerence to thy holy name and precious bloud, giue vs leaue to diſcouer the height of their iniquity, which ſtill goeth forward in more horrible and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner: for thus ſings the Ieſuit.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:9548:26"/>
            <q>
               <l>Lac <hi>Matris miſcere volo cum ſanguine nati,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non poſſum Antidoti nobilore frui.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <q>
               <l>And of her <hi>Milke</hi> mixt with his bloud Ile make,</l>
               <l>The ſoueraign'ſt Cordiall ſinfull ſoule can take.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So now <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> ſhall haue ſatisfaction, (if there were a fault afore) for if he complaine that the <hi>Mother</hi> of his fleſh, a woman and a creature, haue the right hand when <hi>himſelfe</hi> and his merits muſt take the left or none, heere they will make him amends, for that he may haue no cauſe to complaine, for want of place or precedence, her milke and his bloud will hee mingle both together, and ſo make a ſoueraigne compound cordiall for his ſoule. But what? a mixture of <hi>milke</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> of the Bloud of God with the Milke of a <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> and is now the bloud of the <hi>Lambe of God</hi> but one of the ſimples in that cordiall Antidote, that muſt both reſtore and preſerue the life of mans ſoule? <hi>ye hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens be aſtonied at this,</hi> ſo may we well ſay, for ſo ſaid the Prophet at a matter of fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re leſſe wonder, hearken O Chriſtendome, and all ye people, nations, &amp; languages to whom the bleſſed name of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: that poore <hi>paſchal Lambe</hi> of the Iewes that was but a ſhadow of our Sauiour, the Signe and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in ſome ſort the meanes and inſtrument of the Iſraelites temporall preſeruation, might not, nay
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9548:27"/> needed not to haue any thing mingled with the bloud <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 5. <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </note> thereof, but the <hi>bloud</hi> alone being <hi>ſprinckled on their dores,</hi> deliuered them from the ſtroke of the deſtroying Angel: this was their Paſſeouer, and ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Chriſt our Paſſeouer is ſacrificed for vs:</hi> ſhall this then be <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7</note> true, of their Paſſeouer, a Lambe taken out of the fold &amp; flock, &amp; only dedicated by Gods inſtirution, &amp; ſhal not the bloud of our Paſſeouer the Lambe of God, God &amp; man Ieſus Chriſt (whoſe Godhead is conſubſtantiall and coequall with the father, and his humanity perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and indiuiſibly vnited to the deity) being <hi>ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on our hearts &amp; ſoules,</hi> ſuffice to preſerue them from the infernall ſtroake of hell and damnation, vnleſſe it be mingled with the <hi>milke</hi> of a creature? pardon this blaſphemy O bleſſed Ieſus Chriſt, if it bee not a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt the holy Ghoſt, and a deſpighting of the ſpirit of grace: pardon it in as many of them as do not ſinne vnpardonably, for thy mercies ſake. Amen.</p>
            <p>But ſay (I pray thee) tell vs in good earneſt, (If ſo we may preſume to call a Ieſuites Proctor to his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere) is there not a more ſoueraigne Antidote for a ſinfull ſoule, then a mixture &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pound of <hi>Maries</hi> milk &amp; Chriſt his <hi>bloud?</hi> chen tell vs who can make this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? who hath the skill ſufficient for this confection who giues the true <hi>doſſe?</hi> who appoints the <hi>quantities, Mithridates</hi> and <hi>triacles</hi> for the body are not compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for euery <hi>conceit,</hi> nor matters for euery hand to make, but rather beſeeming the skilfulleſt, and require the ouerviewing eye of the whole Colledge of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhall then the heauenly Antidote of the ſoule be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9548:27"/> compounded without a heauenly Phyſition? ſay then (Man) if thou dare ſtand to thy deedes, who was the Phyſition that preſcribed and gaue thee this receipt, was it <hi>God the Father,</hi> the foundation of holineſſe and happineſſe? himſelfe ſaith no, for thus proclaimed hee twiſe from Heauen of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>This is my welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>At his baptiſme Mat.</hi> 17. <hi>At his transfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſonne in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> In none as in him, nay in none, no not in his Mother, but in, for, and by him. Thus the Father of Heauen hath teſtified that the bloud of the ſonne is one ſufficient &amp; ſoueraigne ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for a Heauenly Methridate. Now ſhow thou, (and take the Pope to helpe thee) where euer hee teſtified ſo much of her milke: but if no ſuch thing, nay nothing at all, then he was not the Phyſition that preſcribed this mixture.</p>
            <p>Who then, was it Chriſt himſelfe the Sonne of God and the Sonne of this woman? No, for of himſelfe hee ſaith, <hi>My fleſh is</hi> (ſpirituall) <hi>meate indeed,</hi> and <hi>my bloud is</hi> (heauenly) <hi>drinke indeede:</hi> but of her he ſaith that euery <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.</note> true beleeuing Chriſtian, <hi>is his mother</hi> (as well as ſhee) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12 46</note> in the beſt ſence, and much more then ſhee, had ſhee beene no more but the mother of his fleſh: ſurely then if this bee a lawfull mixture, which this Papiſt makes, the ſonne was much to blame to ſay ſo much of his owne <hi>bloud,</hi> that it is <hi>drinke indeede,</hi> and that it giues the <hi>drinkers eternall life,</hi> &amp;c. and not one word of his mothers milke: Not a word ſayd I? I recall that, for when once a certaine woman hearing him preach, not for any thing ſhee ſaw in her, but for the powerfull and <hi>gracious words,</hi> that came from him, would haue had
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9548:28"/> her <hi>wombe bleſſed that bare him &amp; her Paps that gaue him</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 27. 28</note> 
               <hi>ſucke:</hi> (the worſt whereof is better then her milke) he inſtantly anſwered her, <hi>that much more bleſſed was euery man that heard Gods Word and kept it.</hi> If no extraordinary bleſſednes belong to the wombe that bare him (in that reſpect onely, becauſe it bare him carnally) If none to the <hi>wombe</hi> or <hi>paps,</hi> which ſhall endure for euer, then how much leſſe to the <hi>milke</hi> that fed him, which is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed &amp; ſhall be no more: If Chriſt would not match her <hi>wombe</hi> or <hi>paps</hi> with a man that feared God, what will he ſay to them that make <hi>her milke</hi> a match for <hi>his owne bloud,</hi> the milke being a matter farre inferiour, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wombe or paps. Thus they may ſee that Chriſt is not a fit Phiſition to make this mixture.</p>
            <p>What then was the holy Ghoſt the Phyſition that fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this receipt?</p>
            <p>No, for hee by his diuine power, conceiued Chriſt in that holy and miraculous manner, that Chriſt was fully without originall ſinne, and therefore his bloud might well be a pure and perfect ſimple to make the <hi>Aqua Caeleſtis</hi> that muſt quicken dead ſoules: let them approue as much of her if they can: they ſpeake and write that ſhee was conceiued without ſinne originall, and haue a holy day for it, but they can not prooue it. It is an Article of our faith, and grounded on plaine words of Scripture, that Chriſt was conceiued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">Learned Papiſts hold that the Popes Bulls and the decree of the counſell of Baſill do not conclude it as an article of faith.</note> out ſinne: and though the Whoore of Babilon, affirme as much of her, yet was ſhe yet neuer ſo impudent, as to conclude it an Article of the faith. Thus God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt, do all diſclaime the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9548:28"/> compoſition of this Antidote, as neither preſcribed nor allowed by them.</p>
            <p>Who then may be imagined to be this Phyſition? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exodus</hi> 12.</note> was it <hi>Moſes?</hi> no, for hee allowed nothing to be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the bloud of the Paſcall Lambe: was it <hi>Eſaias?</hi> no, for hee auoucheth that <hi>with his ſtripes we are healed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.</note> and his ſtripes were not without bloud.</p>
            <p>Was it <hi>Zacharia?</hi> no, for he teacheth that <hi>the Church</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zacha</hi> 9. 11.</note> 
               <hi>is ſaued by the bloud of her couenant,</hi> which is grounded only on the <hi>Mesſias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any other Prophet, let them ſhew him: was it <hi>Iohn Baptiſt:</hi> no, for he reſtified that not the Mother of his Lord, but his Lord Ieſus Chriſt was <hi>that Lambe of God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 1. 29.</note> 
               <hi>that takes away the ſinnes of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul?</hi> no, for he teacheth the <hi>Romans,</hi> that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 24. 25.</note> 
               <hi>We are iuſtified freely by his bloud:</hi> (behold yee <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> there is no milke) and the <hi>Epheſians</hi> that <hi>we haue redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>through his bloud:</hi> (yet there is no milke) and the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losſians,</hi> that <hi>he ſet vs at peace tbrough the bloud of his croſſe</hi> not the <hi>milke</hi> of her paps: and the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> that not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 9. 12.</note> with any milke, but <hi>with his owne bloud he obtained eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall redemption for vs:</hi> to conclude, 13. times at leaſt in his Epiſtles doth hee mention the bloud of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, and with the ſame honour as afore, &amp; not once did he ſo much as name our Ladies milke: ſurely either this was an intollerable omiſſion in Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> not once to name it, elſe, preſumptuous impiety in the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to match it with <hi>bloud</hi> of the ſon of God.</p>
            <p>Then who is it, was it S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter</hi> whome you bragge to be the founder, nay the foundation of your Church to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9548:29"/> and head of your Herarchie? No, that bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle renounceth it, for hee proclaimeth to all the world, that wee are <hi>elected through the ſprinckling of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>bloud of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> heere is no milke: and as wee are <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18.</note> elect and ſanctified, ſo <hi>redeemed alſo not with things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puptible</hi> (therefore not with <hi>milke) but with the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Behold ye Ieſuits and bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Peter</hi> is all in <hi>Bloud, bloud,</hi> he knowes no milke.</p>
            <p>There remaines but one (for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iude</hi> if they name not Chriſts <hi>bloud,</hi> I am much more ſure they name <hi>no milke)</hi> was it S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn the beloued Diſciple,</hi> to whom Chriſt <hi>committed her, (as his mother,</hi> but not his Sauiour?) no verily, for he is plaine, that not the <hi>milke</hi> of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> but the <hi>bloud of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne clenſeth vs from all our ſinnes:</hi> and that there <hi>are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 7</note> 
               <hi>three which beares witneſſe on earth, the ſpirit &amp; water &amp; bloud:</hi> behold three witneſſes on earth of our ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <note place="margin">1. <hi>John</hi> 5. 8.</note> and redemption, and of them <hi>bloud</hi> is one, but <hi>milke</hi> is none, yea <hi>water</hi> is, and yet <hi>milke</hi> is not: ſurely if the fathers of the <hi>ſociety</hi> of the <hi>inquiſition</hi> might bee Iudges, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> were ſure to be cenſured to remember <hi>water,</hi> and forget <hi>milke.</hi> But ſee how S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> and the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> differ, they dare match and mixe her <hi>milke</hi> with his <hi>bloud,</hi> hee will neither mixe nor matchit ſo much as with the <hi>water,</hi> ſhewing that the very <hi>water iſſuing out of his precious ſide,</hi> was more of worth and value, then all her milke, euen that which fed the fleſh of Chriſt when he was an Infant: Nay, the Apoſtle hath <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. 5.</note> nor yet done, but tels vs that <hi>Chriſt loued vs and waſhed vs</hi> (not in his mothers milke, but) <hi>in his bloud:</hi> and that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9548:29"/> the <hi>Robes of the Saints are made white</hi> (euen white, &amp; yet not in white milke, but) in the red <hi>Bloud of the Lambe:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 7. 14</note> See heere, if euer milke had beene apt it had been here, if euer it had beene ſeaſonable to haue named it, here had been the place: for what ſhould make white, <hi>milke</hi> or <hi>bloud?</hi> and yet the <hi>whiteneſſe</hi> that muſt cloath the Saints; muſt be dyed not in the <hi>milke</hi> of our Lady, but in the <hi>bloud</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt, if his beloued and bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi> nay if his owne holy word may be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. If none of all theſe, was it then her ſelfe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed this portion and made this mixture? no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly: They ſay we diſhonor &amp; diſgrace her, yet I dare venture euen my ſoule vpon it, that her heart neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to ſuch a thought, as to match &amp; mixe her milke with his bloud: for ſeeing the <hi>Angel</hi> ſaith ſhe was <hi>belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>of God,</hi> I am ſure that no creature can be beloued of God, that durſt offer to match the beſt thing in him (if it were his very harts <hi>bloud)</hi> with the <hi>bloud</hi> of his ſon; no his ſoule would hate him, his wrath breake out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him &amp; his vengeance purſue him to deſtruction. Farre ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſhe from ſo vile a thought: nay, <hi>her ſoule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke</hi> 1. 47</note> 
               <hi>in him her Sauiour,</hi> ſo farre was ſhe from making her ſelfe in any part a Sauiour of her ſelfe: yea rather, if a Saint in heauen doth heare a blaſphemy on earth, then doubtleſſe that bleſſed ſoule of hers; that <hi>magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Sonne and reioyced in him</hi> as her Sauior, will neuer ceaſe to cry and call vpon him, to reuenge ſo high im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety: which is ſo much more hainous, in as much as they make the <hi>mother</hi> the diſhonourer of the <hi>ſonne.</hi> And if her prayers bee as powerfull with him as their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9548:30"/> teacheth, aſſuredly ſhe will net ceaſe to prouoke, his iuſtice againſt them, til ſhe haue laid their tottering kingdome flat on the earth, for erecting vp her as an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll againſt her ſon, and for mixing the vertue of her milke with the the merits of his precious bloud.</p>
            <p>Thus then, if neither God the <hi>Father,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> nor the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> nor <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor the <hi>Prophets,</hi> nor the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> nor the bleſſed <hi>Virgin</hi> her ſelfe, did any of them preſcribe this portion? nor make this mixture: It followeth, that either the Diuell was the deuiſer of it, or elſe that they framed it out of their owne braines and therefore to be iudged <hi>Mountebankes,</hi> and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deceiuers: who make ſhew to the world, they haue a confection of miraculous vertue, when indeed it is a perfect poyſon to all that take it: for if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay true, that <hi>if we ioyne circumciſion to Chriſt, Chriſt ſhal profit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galath.</hi> 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>vs nothing:</hi> then without all controuerſie, if we mixe the <hi>milke</hi> of a creature with the <hi>blood</hi> of the Mediator, that <hi>blood</hi> of his hath loſt the vertue, and ſhall profite vs nothing: And thus the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſpunne a faire threed: ſhe will needes haue both the <hi>ſonne</hi> and the <hi>mother</hi> to be hers, in ſuch a manner, as ſhe hath loſt them both, and made them both her enemies, the mother to be her bitter <hi>accuſer,</hi> and the ſonne to bee her angry <hi>Iudge.</hi> But thus hath God in Iuſtice blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her, that whereas for theſe 2. or 300. yeares paſt, ſhe came to this height of blaſphemous deuotion, as <note place="margin">This is ordinary in many of their books eſpecially Bernar. de Buſ. to his mariale: and reuelationes Brige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; others</note> to truſt more the piety of the Mother, then the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the ſonne, &amp; often to appeale from him to her: Now ar laſt by this dealing they haue taken the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9548:30"/> courſe to turne her againſt them alſo, and to make her curſe and abhor them and their ſuperſtition, who dare make her name and her Milke to bee the diſho nourers of her Sonne, her Sauiour, and his precious bloud.</p>
            <p>Thus we haue heard and ſeene the ſtrangeſt peece of Phyſicke, and moſt vnequall mixture that yet was euer heard of, The <hi>bloud</hi> of God, and <hi>milke</hi> of a woman are mixed to make a cordiall potion, But now what will this potion do, what is the operation of it, hearken to the <hi>Mountebancks proclamation,</hi> and he will tell you.</p>
            <p>Thus he cries.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vulnera reſtituent turpem vlceribus mendicum,</l>
               <l>Teſta cui ſaniem reddere ſola poteſt:</l>
               <l>Vbera reficient Iſmaelem ſitientem</l>
               <l>Quem Sara non patitur, quem neque nutrit Agar,</l>
               <l>Illa mihi ad Peſtem procul &amp; procul expungendam</l>
               <l>Iſta mihi ad long as eua litura febres.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Theſe <hi>wounds</hi> the ſores do clenſe and cure full well,</l>
               <l>Which none can dreſſe but ſcrape them with a ſhell,</l>
               <l>Theſe <hi>breſts</hi> the fainting <hi>Iſmael</hi> well would cheriſh,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Sara</hi> would not, and <hi>Hagar</hi> could not nouriſh</l>
               <l>The <hi>firſt</hi> from me expels all peſtilence,</l>
               <l>The <hi>ſecond</hi> driues all lingring Feauers hence.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now he tells vs what his Phyſicke will doe, and that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9548:31"/> particularly in both his ſimples, the <hi>bloud</hi> and the <hi>milke:</hi> and as for the one of them that is the <hi>bloud and wounds</hi> of the Mediator, if hee had aſcribed much more vnto them, he might haue paſt with praiſe (for vs) for hee cannot ſufficiently extoll the merit &amp; vertue of them, but as for the other, that is the <hi>milke</hi> of a woman, (tho it be the bleſſed virgin) or a confection of both, there he ſheweth himſelfe both impious in making ſuch a mixture, as alſo a vaine deceiuer, proclayming great and ſoueraigne power in that which is nothing worth; for I ſay againe, if it bee true that to him that ioyneth <hi>circumciſion to Chriſt, Chriſt is no Sauiour:</hi> then we dare boldly ſay: To him that ioyneth a creatures <hi>milke</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quallity <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galath.</hi> 5</note> with Chriſts <hi>bloud,</hi> that <hi>bloud</hi> of Chriſt is of no vertue: for <hi>circumciſion is of the fathers,</hi> nay it was <hi>Gods owne ordination.</hi> But her <hi>milke</hi> is meerely apart (and no eſſentiall part) of her body which is a creature, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 17</note> as for the mixture of it with his <hi>bloud,</hi> it is an impious deuice of prophane pollititians, not derogating from the dignity, but euen quite abolliſhing the glory of the mediator: then if his paſſion may not bee ioyned with circumciſion, may his bloud be mixdd with her milke? But what is that hee proclaymeth <hi>vulnera reſtituent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chriſts wounds wil reſtore &amp; heale the ſpiritual ſores of a ſinful Lazar,</hi> we beleeue it will, they will do ſo &amp; much more; yet for not his ſake that ſaith ſo, for wee know that <hi>deuils</hi> themſelues for a vantage would beare witnes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8</note> to Chriſt. But for his ſake that ſaid. <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgresſions, He was broken for our iniquities, the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſement</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>of our peace was vpon Him, &amp; with his Stripes are</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:9548:31"/> 
               <hi>we healed:</hi> and for his owne ſake eſpecially, who ſaid it and did it, <hi>I lay downe my life for my ſheepe.</hi> Thus he hath ſaid well and truly of the wounds; but the wounds of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.</note> Chriſt will not ſerue his turne: He therefore addeth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vbera reficient, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Pappes <hi>will quench and refreſh thirſty ſoules.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And will they ſo? who taught you this Diuinitie? will a creatures Paps quench and ſatisfie that <hi>ſoule that hungreth and thirſteth after righteouſneſſe?</hi> Say yee chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of iniquity, haue you not read <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet, who tels vs <hi>He</hi> was deſpiſed, <hi>He</hi> was afflicted, <hi>Hee</hi> was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.</note> broken, <hi>He</hi> was plagued, and all for vs: <hi>His ſtripes healed vs,</hi> and not a word of her nor her <hi>Milke,</hi> but all of <hi>Him, his ſtripes and his wounds:</hi> what will yee ſay, wanted he <hi>knowledge</hi> of her worthineſſe? or <hi>deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to her deſerts? <note place="margin">Indeed the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue taught ſo in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>former times as ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mariale.</note> Can yee ſay the firſt without blaſpemy to God? or the ſecond without iniury to the Prophet? could it bee he knew not <hi>her</hi> who knew her <hi>ſonne?</hi> could hee foreſee <hi>him</hi> and not <hi>her?</hi> or could any ſuch miſtery be kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him who ſpake and wrote, <hi>as hee was inſpired by Gods ſpirit?</hi> and to conclude, was it not he that ſaith, <hi>Behold a Virgin ſhall conceiue and bring forth a ſonne, euen Emanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> ſo that its plaine as the Prophet knew a <hi>Meſsias</hi> ſhould come and ſhould ſaue his people by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them; ſo alſo he foreſaw and knew he ſhould be borne of a <hi>virgin:</hi> If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prophet had knowledge of her, dareye ſay he wanted due deuotion? and yet
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9548:32"/> one of theſe you muſt ſay, and for want of one of theſe you muſt condemne him, who names none but Chriſt, or elſe your ſelues, who dare mixe her <hi>milke with his bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is this all? No,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Illa mihi ad peſtem—</l>
               <l>Iſta mihi ad febres.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>One can heale ſpirituall <hi>peſtilence,</hi> the other ſpirituall <hi>Feuers;</hi> ſee what difference there is by their religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt her <hi>milke</hi> and his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loud:</hi> are not theſe men great and deuout honorers of Chriſt, and his ſuffering that can finde other helpes to heale their ſoules beſides his bloud? But if it be thus that both can heale ſo wel, how comes it to paſſe they haue ſo many ſick ſoules in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, euen ſick of all ſpirituall diſeaſes, eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by their owne doctrine and dayly practiſe, it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant they can neither want the one nor the other of theſe 2. ſimples: for firſt they ſay, they make Chriſts bloud euery day, then they haue bloud at hand conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: If they ſay that the Laytie may not haue that, but only their Prieſts (who indeede drinke it vp all) yet then they may take their Ladies <hi>milke</hi> whereof (if themſelues ſay true) they haue ſo much in ſeuerall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ſome that liued 100. yeares agoe doe write, that <note place="margin">Eraſinus and others haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully then I doe.</note> in thoſe dayes, it was more then a woman vpon one child can giue out, though the child ſucked none at all: If that that is kept, and ſhewed and worſhipped in ſo many Cities of <hi>Italy, France, Spaine, Germany,</hi> bee not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9548:32"/> her <hi>milke,</hi> then where is the truth and honeſty of that Religion, ſo to deceiue the world? if it bee, then why are their ſoules ſo full of ſpirituall diſeaſes? why are they not healed, ſeeing this Ieſuite teacheth that <hi>it will heale as well as Chriſts bloud?</hi> as well as Chriſts bloud wil ſome ſay, why do you them that wrong? they are neuer ſo wicked to ſpeake ſuch blaſphemy, No? then iudge by that which followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ira vomit flammas fumat que libidinis Aetna?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Suffocare <hi>queo</hi> Sanguine, Lacte <hi>queo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Liuor inexpleta rubigine ſaeuit in artus?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Detergere queo</hi> Lacte, cruore <hi>queo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vanus honos me perpetua prurigine tentat?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Exaturare queo</hi> Sanguine, Lacte <hi>queo.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>That is,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Let <hi>Ire</hi> belch fire, and luſt like <hi>Aetna</hi> flame,</l>
               <l>Chooſe either <hi>milke</hi> or <hi>blood,</hi> doth quench the ſame,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Enuies</hi> ruſt canker my heart about,</l>
               <l>This <hi>milke,</hi> that <hi>bloud,</hi> either will fetch it out,</l>
               <l>Or do <hi>vaine glorious</hi> paſſions ſtuffe me ſtill,</l>
               <l>Either with <hi>milke</hi> or <hi>bloud</hi> the ſame Ile kill.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Heere iudge and ſpare not (without all partiallity,) whether that I ſaid be not true, that <hi>her milke</hi> will heale as well as Chriſts <hi>bloud,</hi> and this they affirme, not in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall tearmes but in plaine particulars: if, ſaith he, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> ſwell, if <hi>Luſt</hi> inflame me, <hi>bloud</hi> will quench them &amp;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9548:33"/> ſo will <hi>milke:</hi> are there two ſtronger <hi>pasſions,</hi> two more conquering <hi>corruptions,</hi> two more raging and raigning ſinnes then Anger and Luſt? yet euen theſe two are quenched &amp; conquered by her <hi>milke</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſts bloud:</hi> hearken ye Children of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Sinagogue, hearken I ſay what inſtruction your father giues you, heare I pray (but learne it not) a creatures milke will clenſe your Soules from ſin, as well as your Sauiours bloud: O ſpirit of error and blaſphemy, whether wilt thou goe? O Romiſh impiety, when wilt thou make an end? wilt thou not ceaſe till thou haſt puld downe the fire of Gods fury, from heauen vpon thee? O <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon we would haue healed thee, but thou wilt not be healed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io:</hi> 51. 9.</note> for who can heale him that will needes kill himſelfe? ſo who can heale thee, whoſe blaſphemy hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; yet benummed thy heart, gone ouer thy head &amp; is <hi>aſcended vp to heauen,</hi> &amp; in the preſence of God crieth vengeance vpon thee; &amp; as for you ſeduced ſoules (my deare cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try-men) you who are deceiued with ſhewes of holineſſe and deuotion, behold heere a peece of Popiſh holineſſe, and of the doctrine of their deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>the ſinnes of the ſoule are clenſed and taken away as well by a creatures milke as by Chriſt his bloud!</hi> is this the <hi>catholike</hi> Doctrine they brag ſo much of? is this the <hi>catholike</hi> Church that teacheth ſuch diuinity? is this the chaire of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; the <hi>ſeate</hi> that cannot erre? If it be ſo, then what didſt thou meane thou S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, to teach that it was <hi>Ieſus Chriſt that faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. 5</note> 
               <hi>that firſt begotten from the dead, &amp; that Prince of the Kings of the earth</hi> (euen hee, and not any creature) <hi>who</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:9548:33"/> 
               <hi>hath loued vs and waſhed vs from our ſins in his bloud:</hi> ſure either muſt you recant this Doctrine, els they that boaſt themſelues to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſucceſſors of thy brother <hi>Peter</hi> may be aſhamed of theirs, who tell vs that <hi>our ſinnes are waſht away in her milk as wel as by his bloud:</hi> and you that are the dutifull and deuoted children of that Romiſh ſeate, be Iudges euen your ſelues in this caſe, what can be ſaid heereunto: how can it ſtand with ſcripture, or with the tenor of true catholike faith? or how can it any way be defended that a <hi>creatures</hi> milke can quench the fire of ſinne in the ſoule as well as Chriſt his <hi>bloud?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can ye ſay that heere is onely aſcribed to her and her <hi>milke,</hi> a <hi>deriued</hi> vertue from another, and that the <hi>originall</hi> and fundamentall power, is onely and wholy in Chriſt and his bloud? if it were ſo, it were leſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill (though Chriſt Ieſus may not, nor will not beſtow the prerogatiues of his Mediatorſhip on any creature) but looke and weigh ouer the words again and againe, expound them with any fauour that the words may beare, and you ſhall not ſee the leaſt difference.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Suffocare queo</hi> Sanguine <hi>Lacte queo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Detergere queo</hi> Lacte Cruore <hi>queo.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>If <hi>Luſt</hi> burne, and <hi>Anger</hi> boyle, <hi>Enuy</hi> fret, <hi>vaineglory</hi> ſwell, I can helpe it with <hi>bloud,</hi> ſo can I with with <hi>milk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> I can helpe it with <hi>milke,</hi> ſo can I with <hi>bloud:</hi> there can be no greater equality made betwixt any two things in the world, then heere they make betwixt this <hi>Bloud</hi> and <hi>Milke.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:9548:34"/>
            <p>Can it be ſaid that the Author is a Poet, and ſaid thus but to make vp the Verſe, which otherwiſe would not haue falne ſo fitly? ſurely no, for a yong verſiſier can ſoone ſhew how the verſes might haue run aſwell as they doe, if hee had not purpoſely laboured to ſort his verſe to his matter, and not the matter to his verſe:</p>
            <p>For thus he might haue ſaid,
<q>
                  <l>Detergere queo ſanguine Chriſte tuo.</l>
               </q> with very little altoration.</p>
            <p>And ſo of the reſt: but hee as truly endeuoured to magnifie the milke as the bloud, and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any neceſſity of the Verſe, gives the ſame power, place, &amp; preheminence, in euery reſpect to the milke as to the bloud: but had he beene as ſound and ſincere a Chriſtian as he is a good Poet, hee might in as good verſes haue giuen all the honour to Chriſt as he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. Therefore (my deare country-men) bee no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſeduced by a Religion ſo fraught with Atheiſme, blaſphemie &amp; impiety: doe but looke into the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Counſels, or Fathers: yea aske the honeſteſt &amp; learnedſt of your owne Religion, (or any except Ieſuits or ſuch other like them, who frame a religion to their owne purpoſes.)</p>
            <p>If this be tollerable Diuinity that the <hi>milke</hi> of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin doth clenſe mans ſoule from ſin as well as <hi>Chriſt his bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it bee not Diuinity but Blaſphemy, no Chriſtian Doctrine but impiety, and yet ſuffered, yet approued
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9548:34"/> in the Romane Church, both by doctrine and practice; then returne to that truth and holy Religion, which out of Gods word, and according to the pureſt antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is eſtabliſhed amongſt vs: and with heart and voice ioyne with vs to imbrace and ſay Amen, to that holy doctrine of bleſſed S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn,</hi> who ſaith it is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1, 56.</note> 
               <hi>that loued vs, and waſhed vs from our ſins in his own bloud to him be glory for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was his Religion, this is ours: oh that it were yours alſo! he ſucked this diuinity out of that bleſſed breſt of Gods Sonne, <hi>whereon he leaned:</hi> and if hee had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 13. 23.</note> ſucked thence this diuinity of the Ieſuites, that the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary waſhed vs from our ſinnes by her milke,</hi> ſurely he would neuer haue concealed it from vs, nor haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued her of the <hi>honour,</hi> nor vs of the <hi>comfort</hi> that thereby might accrew both to her and vs: for he was her <hi>ſonne</hi> by her owne <hi>adoption,</hi> yea her Sonne by the <hi>gift</hi> and nomination of her <hi>ſonne</hi> and Sauiour, yea her Sonne in loue, duty, and all reſpectiueneſſe could hee then, or would he in any ſort obſcure her due glory? would he giue too much to her <hi>ſonne,</hi> and too little to <hi>her?</hi> would he giue all that to her <hi>ſonne,</hi> which in part was <hi>hers?</hi> can this, may this, or dare this be immagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by any Ieſuit? If not, then how dare they extend their deuotion beyond <hi>his,</hi> &amp; aſcribe that to her which he neuer did, yea that to <hi>her,</hi> which he appropriates to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they thinke that <hi>Peter</hi> had more deuotion then <hi>Iohn,</hi> hearken then what he ſaith: <hi>Ieſus Chriſt his owne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 24.</note> 
               <hi>ſelfe bare our ſinnes in his body on the tree:</hi> let the words be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9548:35"/> Pondered, Ieſus Chriſt ſaith hee bare our ſinnes: true (ſay they) but ſo did the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> alſo, No (ſaith <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> he <hi>himſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his owne ſelfe</hi> bare them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea <hi>in his body.</hi> he bare them <hi>in his body:</hi> (ſay they) that is true, but hee beares them in his <hi>myſticall body,</hi> in his members, much more therefore in his <hi>mother,</hi> which is more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny members of his body: nay, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter, hee bare our ſinnes his owne ſelfe in his body:</hi> but what body? euen that body that was <hi>on the Tree:</hi> therefore if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter</hi> preach true diuinity, then is this doctrine of your tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher hainous blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>All that may bee imagined for their defence at the beſt is this, that all this is but <hi>poeticall,</hi> &amp; hyperbolicall, or proceedes from the paſſion &amp; height of deuotion: but that in truth and earneſt he aſcribes all to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; to his bloud, makes his prayers to him, and puts the confidence of his heart in him alone: but leaſt any man ſhould haue the leaſt ſuſpition of him this way, or thinke ſo good a thought of him, he deales yet more plainely and to preuenr all ſuch thoughts and obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he makes his prayer both to the Moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r and the Sonne, without any difference in the world, to the one for her <hi>milke,</hi> to the other for his <hi>bloud:</hi> for thus hee ſaith.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> parens <hi>et nati meis adverti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e votis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lac <hi>peto depereo</hi> ſanguinem <hi>vt rumque volo.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Mother and Sonne giue eare to what I craue,</l>
               <l>I beg this <hi>milke,</hi> that <hi>bloud</hi> and both would haue.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:9548:35"/>
            <p>Heere is plaine dealing, it is not the Sonne and his bloud that will ſerue his turne hee muſt alſo haue the Mother and her milke, is not this good catholike doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and deuotion? but further is not this ſtrange to ſee how he marſhalls them in the order of his iudgement and affection? he prayeth to the mother and the ſonne: but firſt to the <hi>mother,</hi> hee will haue both milke and bloud, but firſt <hi>milke:</hi> thus <hi>Mary</hi> hath the precedence of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and her milke of his bloud: But you will ſay it is not that hee ſo eſteemes them in his iudgement, but only for the neceſſity of of the verſe: the anſwere is that a grammer ſcholler, can ſoone ſhew how the verſe is as good, and giue Chriſt his precedence, as it is doing him this wrong:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ergo Nate parenſque meis aduertite votis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But he ſtill keeping Chriſt in <hi>wardſhip</hi> and vnder age, held it not fit that he ſhould haue the place before his Mother onely, and therefore without all neceſſity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen wittingly and wilfully, he puts Chriſt in the ſecond place. But now let vs haſten to an end of this (if it be not endleſſe and bottomleſſe) impiety.</p>
            <p>Vpon theſe fearefull premiſes thus he proceedes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paruule maternis medius qui ludis in vluis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et tua iam comples vbera, iam vacuas:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quid me reſpectas obliqua tuentibus hirquis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roboris in Coelum pilhabet inuidia.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:9548:36"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saepe quidem dixti, noxis offenſus iniquis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tune me as</hi> mammas, <hi>Improbe tune me as?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nolo tuas ô nolo tuas puer auree</hi> mammas:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ſunt tam duri, tam grauis or is homo:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed tantum</hi> lateris <hi>pluat vnica &amp; vnica ſtilla:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et ſaltem a dextrae vulnere gutta pluat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Se nihil è dextra vis impluere, implue</hi> laeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si nihil è laeua, de pede ſanguis eat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si tibi non placio vulnus mihi vulnera danto</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercedem danto vulnera, ſi placeo.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>That is,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Youngling that in thy mothers armes art playing,</l>
               <l>Sucking her breſts ſometimes, and ſometimes ſtaying,</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou view me with that looke of ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Its forceleſſe Enuy that gainſt thee is borne.</l>
               <l>Oft haſt thou ſaid, being angry at my ſinne,</l>
               <l>Dareſt thou deſire the <hi>teates</hi> my foode lies in?</l>
               <l>I will not, oh I dare not (Noble child)</l>
               <l>Duty from me is not ſo far exild:</l>
               <l>But one, euen one poore drop I doe implore,</l>
               <l>From thy right <hi>hand</hi> or <hi>ſide,</hi> I aske no more.</l>
               <l>If neither: from thy <hi>left hand</hi> let one fall,</l>
               <l>Nay from thy foote rather then none at all,</l>
               <l>Doſt thou diſlike me? let thy wounds me wound,</l>
               <l>But pay my due, if I in grace be found.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now from blaſphemy he proceedes to plaine Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, not fearing to expoſe the greateſt myſteries of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:9548:36"/> Chriſtian faith, and euen our bleſſed Sauiour himſelfe, to the rediculous &amp; ſcornefull contempt of prophane men: Speaking vnto Chriſt, God c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aequall with the father, and whoſe very humanity raineth now in glory at Gods right hand, as to a ſeely Infant in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers armes: and to him whoſe very humanity is fedde with the glorious preſence and contemplation of the deity, as to a poore <hi>child ſucking</hi> his Mother breſts: ſuch conceits are common, and ſuch words and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings riſe with thm, of our bleſſed Sauiour, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but with the Title of <hi>Queene of heauen, Lady of Angels,</hi> the <hi>gate of Paradiſe,</hi> the <hi>fountaine of mercy,</hi> or ſome ſuch other titles, fitting none but him that is God, or at leaſt ſhee is alwayes a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding Mother, and he an Infant gouerned, and an obedient child: But let vs conſider his words a little better. <hi>Paruule &amp;c, youngling</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou pretty babe, thou playeſt in thy mothers armes, and ſometimes ſuckes her breſts till they be emptie, and againe ſtayeſt till they bee full, &amp;c.</hi> Is this good and ſound Diuinity, that Chriſt our Redeemer is now this preſent yeare, at <hi>Halla</hi> in <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brant,</hi> an <hi>Infant playing in his mothers armes, and ſucking her breſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it bee ſo, then ſure S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> was much to blame to teach vs, that euen <hi>the man Ieſus Chriſt, after he had</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 12</note> 
               <hi>offred one ſacrifice for ſinnes, ſitteth for euer</hi> (not in his mothets armes, but) <hi>at his Fathers right hand:</hi> and what doing? not playing in her armes, nor ſucking her breſts, but there <hi>he euer liueth to make interceſsion for vs.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25.</note> Interceſſion! to whom? not to <hi>her</hi> in whoſe armes
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9548:37"/> they will make him play, but <hi>to him, at whoſe right hand he ſitteth for euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And much more to blame S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> who (not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing, it ſeemes what doctrine his pretended ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor would teach after him) teacheth vs that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt is at Gods right hand, gone into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to whom Angels, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 22.</note> 
               <hi>and might are ſubiect.</hi> Are Angels, powers &amp; might ſubiect to him? &amp; muſt he be ſubiect to a mortall &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane creature? Nay, is he now an <hi>Infant,</hi> playing in his mothers armes, and hanging on her breſts? is not this good Catholike Romiſh <hi>doctrine?</hi> and is not this good pure Romiſh <hi>deuotion,</hi> to pray to him who is God of glory, &amp; whoſe manhood is now at Gods right hand, Angels and powers ſubiect to him, in ſuch words as theſe: <hi>Thou pretty Child that playeſt in thy mothers armes, and hangeſt at her breſts?</hi> Is this a ſalutation fit for the ſon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 23</note> of God, who is the <hi>Sonne conſecrated for euer?</hi> the <hi>heire all things.</hi> the <hi>brightneſſe of Gods glory, and the ingrauen forme of his perſon?</hi> or is this a Chriſtian like deſcription of him, who <hi>hauing by himſelfe purged our ſinnes, ſitteth at the right hand of the Maieſty in the higheſt places?</hi> But this is naturall to Popiſh Religion, to diſgrace the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator</hi> they care not how, ſo that they may aduance ſome creatures, and magnifie their owne deuiſes: but though they neuer ſo much abuſe moſt of Gods <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> and nullifie the very Offices of the Mediatour: Yet me thinks they ſhould be a little fearefull how they touch the <hi>Perſon</hi> it ſelfe of the Mediator and ſonne of God, and ſhould ſhrinke and ſhame to expoſe the perſon of Ieſus Chriſt, to the baſe conceit of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9548:37"/> for what can the carnall man, much more the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> the <hi>Turke,</hi> and the <hi>Iewe</hi> imagine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he that is hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pretended Vicar ſuffers his followers to ſpeake and write of him, and pray to him, as a <hi>playing child,</hi> and <hi>ſucking Infant,</hi> and to deſcribe him in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours as a very child, greeuing and crying that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould <hi>touch his mothers Paps</hi> but onely himſelfe? alas what will this Religon of Rome do at laſt? the <hi>word</hi> of God and <hi>Sacraments</hi> and other his holy <hi>ordinances</hi> they haue prophaned, the <hi>officer</hi> of the Mediator haue they nullified, and yet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> content: heere they labour to make ridiculous to all irreligious men, the very <hi>perſon</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe: could this bee done by any but thoſe that are the Children of that Mother of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <hi>that ſits vpon the beaſt full of names of blaſphemy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17, 3.</note> ariſe Lord, mainetaine thine owne cauſe, deliuer thy holy Name from that pollution, and thy Religion from that contempt which they bring vpon it. To conclude: it may not be amiſſe heere to obſerue the oppoſition betwixt God in his holy Scripture, and and the Pope in this his Religion.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:9548:38"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The Scripture ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Popery ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is no more to bee knowne after the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 16</note> fleſh.</cell>
                     <cell>Chriſt is yet to be knowne and worſhipped as a child.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The Scripture ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Popery ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt beares vp all things <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3.</note> by his mighty Word.</cell>
                     <cell>Chriſt is now borne in his mothers armes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The Scripture ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Popery ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt ſitteth for euer at the <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 10</note> right hand of God.</cell>
                     <cell>Chriſt is playing in his mothers armes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The Scripture ſaith</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Popery ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt tarrieth at his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 12, 13.</note> right hand, till his enemies bee made his footeſtoole.</cell>
                     <cell>Hee is in Heauen, till it pleaſe the Pope to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a Picture at Hall or Sichem.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The Scripture ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Popery ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Without Controuerſye <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16</note> great is the miſtery of godlineſſe that Ieſus Chriſt is receiued vp into glory.</cell>
                     <cell>Without controuerſie that it is no ſuch miſtery, for Chriſt is ſtill in his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers armes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The Scripture ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Popery ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt muſt ſuffer and ſo <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</note> enter into his glory.</cell>
                     <cell>Chriſt after all his ſuffrings, muſt againe bee ſubiect to the infirmities of an Infant.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:9548:38"/>
            <p>Out of all this followeth a concluſion of good vſe: It hath beene often obiected to the Romiſh Church, that they haue not <hi>true Chriſt</hi> left amongſt them, but an Idoll of their owne rearing, erected in their owne car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fancies: now that this is no flaunder, no cauill, no hyperbolicall or figuratiue ſpeech, nor an accuſation forced vpon them againſt their wills, is apparant by their owne doctrine and practiſe in this place: for the <hi>Chriſt</hi> of God and of his Church, is God equall to the father, and can do all things himſelfe: the Chriſt of the Romiſh Church is a Child inferiour to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and may deny her nothing. The <hi>true Chriſt,</hi> being man <hi>grew in ſtature and wiſedome,</hi> and being growne a man, ſo liued and dyed, roſe againe and was glorified, and neuer decreaſed: but <hi>theirs</hi> is now become a child againe and a playing Infant: the true <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſitteth at the right hand of God his Father, theirs is borne in the armes of <hi>Mary</hi> his mother.</p>
            <p>Hence the concluſion is euident, that therefore the Romiſh chriſt is not the true Chriſt of God and of the true chriſtian Church. This concluſion I demonſtrate thus: the Title of theſe verſes is this, <hi>To our Lady of Hal, and the Child Ieſus:</hi> this child they ſpeake of, is either Ieſus Chriſt indeed or it is not: if not, then they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime themſelues lyers and impoſtors: if it be, then my concluſion ſtands good: for this Ieſus in all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named reſpects, and many more, differeth from the true Ieſus and Sauiour of Chriſtian men: let them take whether they will, the better is to bad. But now let vs ſee what is that he ſaith to this child Ieſus.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:9548:39"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid me reſpectas, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why (ſaith he) doeſt thou frowne on me (thou prety child) <hi>art thou angry with me for deſiring thy milke? doeſt thou ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d me that I dare preſume to aske the milke of thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers teates?</hi> this is all the cauſe hee layeth of Chriſt his anger, what ſhould a man ſay to this? what would a Iew ſay, what will an Atheiſt thinke of it? ſurely they will deride and laugh at that Religion that allowes it, if our Chriſt bee ſuch a one as is angry at ſuch a cauſe: But ſay I pray thee thou Romiſh Ieſuite, (thou wanteſt neither wit nor learning to giue anſwere) ſpeakeſt thou in ieſt or earneſt? if in <hi>Ieſt,</hi> then, knoweſt thou with whom thou ieſteſt? conſidereſt thou that it is <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth,</hi> the great one, the holy one of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>whoſe kingdome there ſhall be no end,</hi> hee that is <hi>the brightnes of Gods glory &amp; the engrauen forme of his perſon,</hi> he at whoſe remembrance the diuels tremble, and to whom <hi>all knees bow</hi> in heauen, earth, and hell, and dareſt thou exerciſe thy wit, and whet thy ſtile, &amp; practiſe thy poeticall vaine vpon him? and vnto him that now hauing conquered ſinne, death, and hel? <hi>ſitteth now at the right hand of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, in the higheſt places?</hi> dareſt thou preſent ſuch a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition as this? <hi>O pretty child doe not enuy mee that I ſhould touch thy mothers paps, with which I perceiue thou wilt ſuffer none to play but thy ſelfe: oh be not angry that I long for that which is thine, namly for the milk of thy mothers teates;</hi> didſt thou euer find in Scriptures or ſound antiquity, that any holy man did euer conceiue of him, or ſpeake to him on this faſhion? no for its rather a ſporting ſpeech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it to be ſpoken to a playing <hi>child,</hi> then a ſalutation ſit
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:9548:39"/> to be tendered to the Son of God and Sauiour of the world.</p>
            <p>But if thou ſay thou ſpeakeſt in <hi>earneſt</hi> according to the truth of Religion, and ſoundneſſe of diuinity, then tell me I pray thee in earneſt, is this any part of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith, or is it catholike deuinity, that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is offended with that man that ſhall deſire to touch the Virgin <hi>Maries paps,</hi> or to taſte of her milke (not in this regard that its a thing not poſſible, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede not to be wiſhed by a Chriſtian, but) becauſe they be peculiarly &amp; propperly his paps and his milke, ſtill as they were when hee was an Infant? If this bee Romiſh diuinity, alas for the ſheep that are fed in ſuch paſtures, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ild with ſuch doctrine: for this is funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally both falſe &amp; impious, <hi>falſe,</hi> for if it be true that the holy ſcriptures teach, that Ieſus Chriſt is now no more to be <hi>knowne</hi> nor conceiued of <hi>according to the fleſh,</hi> that is as a meere and mortall man, but as a <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> Man, a ſpirituall conquerour of his enemies, and ſpirituall head of his Church: If this I ſay be true, that hee is no longer, to be knowne as a man, as hee was vpon earth, then it is falſe that he is ſtill to bee concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of and ſpoken vnto as a playing child: Beſides it is impious and irreligious, and a ſtep to Atheiſme to imagine that Chriſt our God &amp; Sauior, is offended for ſuch an imaginary toy as this is, to touch his mothers <hi>paps,</hi> or to deſire her <hi>milke:</hi> &amp; what enemies of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would not loudly laugh at this our <hi>Chriſt</hi> whom we ſo magnifie, that we make him the reſt and comfort of our ſoules, to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a one as hee is heere deſcribed?
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:9548:40"/> namely one that chides him that dare touch his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers paps, for ſo ſaith the verſe:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Tune meas Mammas improbe tune meas?</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dareſt thou deſire the teates, my foode lies in?</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Alas, how ſhall the mouthes of <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Iewes</hi> be ſtopped from blaſpheming, and ſaying: Is this your Chriſt? is this the glory of Chriſtianity? Is this he whom you make a God? are theſe the <hi>ſins</hi> he is offended withall? Surely no wayes can ſuch and fowler blaſphemies bee preuented, but that the Chriſtian world publikely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, condemne, and curſe, this damned doctrine, as being the priuate and impious blaſphemy of the Machiuillian Ieſuits, but not the Catholike doctrine of Chriſtianity: For we cannot deny but there is a <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of vipers,</hi> bred of the corruption and putrifacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an old and ſinfull world; calling themſelues <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> or Prieſts of the ſociety of Ieſus: who as they come neereſt to God in their mouthes; ſo are they in their hearts (if their courſes can diſcouer them) the furtheſt from him. With theſe fellowes it may bee it is a doctrine or a peece of deuotion, that its a great ſin for a man to deſire from Ieſus ſome of his <hi>mothers milk:</hi> but if they be asked who made this a ſin, they muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, themſelues: if what law? euen their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: But as for the catholike and chriſtian Church, <hi>ſhe</hi> doth renounce it.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:9548:40"/>
            <p>But to proceede, is it not ſtrange that a witty and learned Ieſuite, ſhould frame ſuch a ſpeech as this vnto <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for thus to begin, <hi>Oh bleſſed Child why art thou angry at me, and offended with me? oft haſt thou ſaid to me being angry at my ſins, &amp;c.</hi> would put a man in hope that ſome great matter followed: for vpon ſo good a beginning, would not a man preſume that ſome good confeſſion of ſinnes ſhould follow? as this, <hi>I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe O Lord I haue ſinned in ignorance, in ſelfe loue in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in hardneſſe of heart, in incontinency, in mallice, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, in couetouſneſſe in omiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of my duties in commiſsion of euill, &amp;c. for theſe O Lord, and for any of theſe, thou mighteſt ſay vnto mee, thou miſerable wretch, how dareſt thou thus pollute my name, and as farre as in thee lyeth,</hi> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie me againe <hi>by theſe thy ſins? how dareſt thou</hi> duſt and aſhes, <hi>thus vilifie my eternall Law, the curſe whereof thou haſt hereby incurred? how dareſt thou beare my Name, or looke mee in the face, whom thou haſt thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Watſon <hi>the Prieſt his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit often in his Quidlibets. Coſterus in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridio: cap de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aleba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u ſacerd. Sacerdos ſi for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>catur aut de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi concubinam foueat tamet ſi grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſacriligio ſe obitringet Grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us tamen peccat ſi mali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> monitum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahat.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that our eares might haue heard a Ieſuite ſaying thus, and then in reaſon a man would haue expected ſome good concluſion from ſuch a beginning. But why ſhould we looke for either reaſon or religion from a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, (if that be true which their brother <hi>Watſon</hi> the prieſt hath written of them.) To haue ſuppoſed Chriſt to be angry with him for breaking the Morrall Law had beene good diuinity, and no poeticall immagination, but theſe holy Fathers haue no ſuch faults: nay ſee how innocent Lambes the Ieſuits be, that when Chriſt is moſt angry with a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> and rebukes him for ſinne,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:9548:41"/> he hath none to lay to his charge, nor finde any where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>This is alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſended both by Gretſer the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit in his hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ord. Ieſ. and by Ignatius ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er: vid. Ep. Ieſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas. for the points af ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; holy dayes, ſee Tollet in his inſtructio ſacerdotum: &amp; Azorius in his inſtitutiones morales. Sixtus</hi> 5. <hi>made that a ſaint at King I hilips re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (expreſly) of his inuaſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f England in</hi> 88.</note> he is guilty, but a little holy <hi>preſumption,</hi> or rather height of ardent <hi>deuotion,</hi> that hee dare touch the <hi>Paps,</hi> and beg the <hi>milke</hi> of the virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> O fearefull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, O carnall ſelfeloue, O helliſh pride, and well beſeeming the Ieſuiticall broode! is not this the <hi>generation that praiſeth it ſelfe,</hi> and (as Salomon ſaith) <hi>is good in his owne eyes?</hi> But ſay in earneſt, is this all the fault that thou thinkeſt Chriſt can find with thee? then belike there is either no breaches at all of the morrall Law, amongſt Ieſuits, or elſe the breaches of Gods Law, are leſſe ſinnes amongſt them, then are the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of their owne deuiſes, and well may it bee ſo: for he was a Ieſuit who taught that <hi>a Prieſt ſinneth leſſe if he kept a whore, or lye with another mans wife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then if hee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a wife of his owne,</hi> I ſay he was a Ieſuite that wrote it, and he was a Ieſuit that defended it.</p>
            <p>Againe, they teach that its a leſſe ſinne to <hi>ſweare</hi> in common talke by the holy name of God, then it is to <hi>eate an egge</hi> in lent: for the latter ſay they is a <hi>mortal</hi> ſin, the firſt is but a <hi>veniall.</hi> Againe, that hee ſins no more that workes vpon the holy <hi>Saboath</hi> day then hee that workes vpon the feaſt day of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Didace</hi> the Spaniard whom <hi>Sixtus</hi> made a Saint, not yet 20. yeares agoe: they who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e doctrines theſe &amp; ſuch others bee, no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell tho they hold that the breach of of a duty of their owne deuiſing, is a greater ſinne, then the breach of the morrall Law: for ſo muſt hee hold that wrote this, or elſe that Chriſt can find no greater fault in him, but that he durſt beg his mothers milke: or elſe that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:9548:41"/> Chriſt would paſſe by all other faults in compariſon of that, let him chuſe which of the three doth pleaſe him beſt, for one he muſt needs take, or elſe confeſſe that all this while he is but in ieſt.</p>
            <p>I would leaue this point, but that my loue to you (my deare country-men, the Papiſts of England) prouokes me to one word more, to you and for your ſakes.</p>
            <p>Conſider I pray you what theſe men are, who bee the Fathers and founders, at leaſt the guiders and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors of your faith: A generation that knowes no euill by it ſelfe, but this that (I dare ſtand to) is no euill at all, but of their owne making, a generation againſt whom Chriſt hath nothing but this ridiculous allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which you haue heard of: which if it bee true, as they are a ſociety of all the world to be <hi>honoured,</hi> ſo being falſe, they are a broode of Hyppocrites, of all the world to bee <hi>deteſted:</hi> Then ſee how, you are dayly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched by their inchantments, and carried vp and downe as they pleaſe to leade you: but conſider I pray you what wil not thoſe men ſay of themſelues to you in priuate, which ſpeake thus inſolently of themſelues in publike? what meruailous, miraculous, and incredible things wil not theſe fellowes buz into the eares of their Nouices (whome they indeauour to binde Prenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to their <hi>Belzebub?)</hi> who offer to publiſh to the eyes and cenſure of all the world, that Chriſt lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing to their charge vnleſſe it be an extremity of deuotion, to his bleſſed mother: O beloued coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, be not ſeduced by ſuch <hi>impoſtors!</hi> let not ſuch <hi>vipers</hi> eate your hearts; but diſcouer the Hypocrites and ſend them home vnmasked to Hell where they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:9548:42"/> were hatched, for they that dare thus dally with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, no maruell tho they be ſo bold with your ſoules and conſciences, your children and your eſtates and all that belongs to you.</p>
            <p>Now to goe forward, hee hath told vs the great quarrell that Chriſt hath to him, and the hideous fault for which he chides him, that hee offers to touch his <hi>mothers teates,</hi> and will needes haue ſome of her <hi>milke:</hi> but now let vs ſee what he anſwers and how he defends himſelfe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nolo tuas ô nolo tuas puer auree mamas.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>I will not, oh I dare not, golden child:</l>
               <l>Duty from me is not ſo farre exild:</l>
               <l>But one euen one poore drop I do implore.</l>
               <l>From thy right hand or ſide, I aske no more.</l>
            </q>
            <p>To a ſtrange accuſation, heere is a more ſtrange anſwer: for now the tide of his blaſphemy is euen at at the higheſt: the quarrell hee ſuppoſed, Chriſt to haue againſt him, was that hee durſt preſume to touch his <hi>mothers paps,</hi> or deſire to taſte of her <hi>milke:</hi> a fearefull ſinne doubtleſſe, yet neither forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Law nor the Goſpell; but a ſinne of the Popes making. But what is his anſwere hereunto? hee plainely pleads <hi>not guilty,</hi> alledging for himſelfe, that he is not ſo bold, ſo rude, ſo preſumptuous, as to dare to entertaine any ſuch thought, or attempt any ſuch thing, as to touch her ſacred <hi>paps,</hi> or to drinke of that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:9548:42"/> glorious <hi>milke:</hi> no his ambition reacheth not ſo high, he onely prayeth to haue part of his <hi>wounds</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> that he deſireth as being a thing of an inferiour nature and not comparable to the other.</p>
            <p>O miſerable times of ours, that we ſhould liue to ſee that any mans heart ſhould conceiue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any mans tongue vtter, eſpecially any mans penne ſhould publiſh ſuch horrible blaſphemy againſt the bloud and perſon of our Sauiour! what, muſt the Virgin Mary bee firſt compared, afterward equalled, and is not that enough vnles now ſhe be preferred before, and aduanced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Chriſt? is his bloud inferiour to her milke? and is it leſſe preſumption to bee bold with Chriſt then her? whither will Romiſh religion go at the laſt, that already comes to this?</p>
            <p>But to come to a more particular conſideration of the words: the anſwere that here the Ieſuites makes, containes apparantly both abſurdity and impiety, and both in the higeſt degree: The abſurdity appeares in his euident <hi>contradiction</hi> of himſelfe; for now, as tho he had either forgotten or cared not what he ſaid afore he denyeth that which before he ſpake almoſt in euery verſe: dare you not now touch her <hi>Paps,</hi> nor taſte her <hi>milke?</hi> then who was it that afore ſaid: <hi>I am doubtfull whether to take paps or ſide, milke or bloud: If I looke at the Paps, I long for milke: if at the Wounds, I would haue bloud: ſeeing therfore both are ſo good, I will haue both: I will catch the milke with my right hand, the bloud with the left.</hi> Didſt thou this euen now, and now ſaiſt thou <hi>dare not touch it?</hi> Nay, was it not thou that ſaidſt <hi>I will mingle the milke</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:9548:43"/> 
               <hi>of the mother with the bloud of the Sonne,</hi> and ſo make a ſouerainge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pound to heale my ſoule, and now dareſt thou not <hi>touch the milke nor paps?</hi> was it not thy mouth that ſaid, <hi>if Anger, Luſt, or any ſinne vexe my ſoule, bloud will helpe it, and ſo will milke: therefore Mother and Sonne heere my requeſt, I muſt haue milke, I will haue bloud, I will haue both?</hi> and doſt thou now ſay, Oh I will haue <hi>bloud</hi> indeede, but I dare not deſire <hi>milke?</hi> was it then deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>take</hi> it, and <hi>taſte</hi> it, and <hi>drinke</hi> it, and <hi>mingle</hi> it with Chriſts bloud, and apply it to the ſoule, and is it now preſumption to deſire it? can one mouth ſend out ſuch groſe <hi>contradictions?</hi> but let it paſſe, for no abſurdity nor contradiction can bee ſo vile as ſhould euer haue moued mee to haue ſet Pen to paper at this time, (for they are ſufficiently diſcouered already in theſe and other points,) but when diſhonor and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy is offred to the bloud &amp; perſon of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> how can a chriſtian hold his peace? for if that be true which the learned father ſaith, that <hi>in accuſation of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im:</note> 
               <hi>he would haue no man patient,</hi> whereas <hi>hereſie</hi> is but the ſhame &amp; hurt of the man that holds it? then ſure in the caſe of blaſphemy and impiety, touching the very crowne, and ſtriking at the head of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord and redeemer, who can be patient, who can but ſpeak? neither thinke that heerein I challenge ought to my ſelfe aboue my brethren, but knowe contrarywiſe, that though I onely write, who firſt, or with the firſt diſcouered it, yet ſpeake I, and write I in the perſon of many millions more, who all with one heart and voyce deteſt his Romiſh impiety.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:9548:43"/>
            <p>The <hi>impiety</hi> that bewrayes it ſelfe in this anſwere is ſuch as goeth beyond all wee yet heard, and wherein it ſeemes the blaſphemer thought to exceede himſelfe: that we may the better diſcouer it marke the current of his ſpeech: <hi>O Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>oft haſt thou being prouoked with my ſin, rebuked me and ſaid: dareſt thou ſinful wretch preſume to touch my teates or medle with the milk that feeds me?</hi> he anſwereth, <hi>oh no bleſſed child I dare not, nor I will not ſo farre preſume, I neuer was ſo rude, nor ſo vnci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, as to imagine that I might touch thoſe precious Paps, or taſte the bleſſed milk of thy mother: I only beg a litle of thine owne bloud, from thy ſide, thy hand or foote: that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent me:</hi> what is this we heare? you are content to haue <hi>Chriſts Bloud,</hi> but as for the virgin <hi>Maries milk</hi> thou da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt not deſire it what: is her milk more precious, more dainty, more ſacred then the <hi>bloud</hi> of the Mediatour? Yee heauens be aſtonied at this, and all yee creatures of God (in your kinds) renounce and deteſt this hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous blaſphemy. And you (my poore countrymen) that are the deuoted children of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Church, behold heere a peece of Popiſh diuinity a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d deuotion, <hi>a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures milk is of more eſteeme then Chriſt his bloud: a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the power of his ordinary ſauing faith may bee partaker of the benefit of Chriſts bloud, but not of the bleſſed milke of our Lady. The bloud he may boldly challenge, the milke he ſcarce may name: in the bloud, he may diue and waſh his ſoule, the milke he may not preſume to touch:</hi> Oh new diuinity, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merly it ſeemed ſtrange that her <hi>milke</hi> was but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to his <hi>bloud,</hi> but when after it was made equall to it, and mingled with it, and held as fit to heale the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:9548:44"/> ſoule as it that ſeemed incredible, till wee ſaw it: then what is this that now wee heare, that her milke is not only <hi>comparable</hi> nay <hi>equall</hi> but euen <hi>more precious,</hi> more ſacred, more excellent then the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt: Oh miſerable Religion of <hi>Popery!</hi> whether wilt thou draw thy deceiued children in the end? what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thee and thy followers? If the diuels confeſſed that <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth was the Chriſt of God,</hi> that is the onely Sauiour of the world, and the only annointed of God, to be the mediator, and yet for all this are <hi>Diuels</hi> ſtill and no better: then what are they and what a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is that, which makes his <hi>bloud</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo good, ſo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, ſo ſoueraigne, ſo precious as her <hi>milke,</hi> and ſo by conſequent will neither let him bee the onely nor the principall Sauiour. Now the ſame glorious God and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe merrits are debaced, whoſe perſon diſhonoured, and whoſe bloud little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then troden vnder foote, either conuert in mercy, or in iuſtice confound all that ſhall conſent, defend or giue countenance to ſo fearefull a blaſphemy: and the ſame God giue you grace poore ſeduced Engliſh men, to relinquiſh that Religion, which is the Mother of ſuch monſters as vpon this <hi>theater of the Ieſuits,</hi> are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto you: and eſpecially to deteſt that Ieſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Sect, whoſe honour it is to diſhonour Ieſus Chriſt, and who bring vpon <hi>the great Theater of their honor,</hi> the <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſo diſhonoured, as it yet neuer was by any ſect or profeſſion, Turke or Iewe, Atheiſt, or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, diuell or man, ſince the world began.</p>
            <p>But let vs ſee what remaineth.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:9548:44"/>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saepe mihi Babilon patera propina &amp; auro</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingeminatque me is aurib us, euge, bibe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non faciam, vel ſi Coelum miſcebitur Orco</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non faciam, meretrix impia, non faciam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O ſitio tamen, ô vocem ſit is inter cludit:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nate</hi> cruore <hi>ſitem comprime,</hi> lacte <hi>parens.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Oft times doth <hi>Babilon</hi> in gold me proffer,</l>
               <l>Delicious drinke and wooes me to her offer:</l>
               <l>No, no, though heauen &amp; hell ſhould meete, Ile none,</l>
               <l>Ile none vngracious ſtrumpet, hence be gone:</l>
               <l>But ali I thirſt, a drought my breſt doth ſmother,</l>
               <l>Quench me with <hi>bloud</hi> ſweet Son, with <hi>milk</hi> good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</l>
            </q>
            <p>After the diſcourſe imagined (as we heard before) to be betwixt Chriſt and him, containing Chriſts accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his defence touching the high preſumption of being as bold with his mothers <hi>milke</hi> as his <hi>bloud:</hi> now ſodaainely he turnes himſelfe from Chriſt to <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> and ſuppoſeth that <hi>Babilon</hi> that ſpirituall ſtrumpet allures him to her vnlawfull luſts and vild Idolatries, and that her temptations haue beene both frequent &amp; forcible. And ſurely herein we eaſily beleeue him: for what is ſpiritual <hi>Babilon</hi> but the kingdom of ſin &amp; Satan, of impiety, Idolatry, blaſphemy, ſuperſtition, prophanes: and where is that as in Popery, and where to bee found ſo fully as in the bowels of the Popiſh ſtate, whom they well know all the world either clearely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes, or at leaſt iuſtly ſuſpects to be that ſpirituall
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:9548:45"/> 
               <hi>Babilon</hi> ſo fearefully accuſed and condemned in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation. For what City is ſo notoriouſly knowne to ſtand vpon the notable &amp; famous hills as <hi>Rome</hi> is? what City in all the world did <hi>raigne ouer all the Kings of the earth,</hi> then when S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote, but only <hi>Rome?</hi> and the Text ſaith (as plainely as can bee) that the <hi>woman, the great Whore of Babilon the mother of fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, is the great</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel.</note> 
               <hi>City that raigneth ouer the Kings of the earth:</hi> and laſtly there is no place, perſon, ſtate, nor power, in the world, in whom the number of 666. ſo fully concurreth, in ſo many languages, in ſo many reſpects, ſo directly, and with ſo little ſtrayning as in the Popes.</p>
            <p>I wil ſpecifie but few for many: the Pope or none but the Pope challengeth to the principall of the Clergy, in the world, and therefore in the former yeares hath called himſelfe vniuerſall Biſhop, and Paſtor of Paſtors: Now it falls out that this his pride doth proclaime his ſhame to all the world, for the number of the beaſt is in this name, without adding, altering, or any ſtrayning, as hee ſhall find that will reckon.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>D</cell>
                     <cell>V</cell>
                     <cell>X</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>C</cell>
                     <cell>L</cell>
                     <cell>e</cell>
                     <cell>r</cell>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Totall. <hi>666.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Againe the Pope glorieth in this Title and honour, that he is <hi>Gods generall Vicar on earth:</hi> this is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all his pretended power and vſurpation: this he and his imps fight for as for their liues.</p>
            <p>This his ſeduced creatures, Engliſh Prieſts and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, do in England dye for (excepting ſome that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for horrible treaſons) and no maruell, for they know
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:9548:45"/> they loſe all if they loſe this, and yet the Pope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold it, but withall hee muſt haue the number of <hi>the beaſt</hi> ingrauen in his forehead, ſo as he that runnes may reade it: for put downe this Title in the latine tongue, (which is the tongue by him aduanced aboue Greeke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hebrew, wherein hee writes his Letters, giues his lawes and his bulls, and workes all his feares) and it containes the number of the beaſt, and neither more nor leſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>G</cell>
                     <cell>E</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>E</cell>
                     <cell>R</cell>
                     <cell>A</cell>
                     <cell>L</cell>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>V</cell>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell>C</cell>
                     <cell>A</cell>
                     <cell>R</cell>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell>V</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>D</cell>
                     <cell>E</cell>
                     <cell>I.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>T</cell>
                     <cell>E</cell>
                     <cell>R</cell>
                     <cell>R</cell>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell>S.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">totall <hi>666.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Thus its cleere, that as the Pope will needs be Gods generall Vicar on earth, ſo hee cannot haue it, but hee muſt beare the marke and number of the beaſt. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſay hee calls not himſelfe Gods Vicar, but Chriſts Vicar, I anſwere Chriſt is both God &amp; man, and he holdes himſelfe Chriſts Vicar, euen as Chriſt is God, and full little would he thanke him that holds him Chriſts Vicar, only as he is a man: But I anſwere further, that who euer reades his owne decrees &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conſtitutions, ſhall eaſily ſee that hee calls himſelfe ordinarily the Vicar of God, and ſuffers others ſo to ſtile him: and that the world may ſee they haue not reformed it, the Pope that now is, <hi>Paul the</hi> 5. hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:9548:46"/> one of his owne creatures in a Booke dedicated <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tuccij Tuccij patritij luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſis &amp; protonet A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtol: comment in cant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ug:</hi> 606 <hi>In titulo libri.</hi>
               </note> to him, to call him the <hi>Vicar of God.</hi> Thus Thus he will needs be Gods Vicar, but his pride is well paid for, for as hee will be <hi>Gods Vicar</hi> againſt Gods will, ſo God makes him beare the diuels marke, in the number of the beaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne will.</p>
            <p>If therefore it be ſo likely that <hi>Rome is Babilon,</hi> and her doctrines and deceits, ſuperſtitions, and Idolatries, the fornication of that <hi>whore of Babilon,</hi> then wee eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue this to be true, that <hi>oft times did Babilon allure him with her entiſements,</hi> &amp; wooe him to her ſpirituall fornications: ſo hath ſhe done many more, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes with too many.</p>
            <p>But what, with him? No, he will haue none: it is well ſayd. Oh that you would doe as well, that is the worſt we wiſh you <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> though you wiſh vs nothing but fire and gunpowder.</p>
            <p>Oh that you would turne into your ſelues and ſee your error in beleeuing her, and in being deceiued with her inchantments, and <hi>drunke with her fornications</hi> that you would no longer bee the ſonnes of her that is the <hi>mother of abhominations</hi> leaſt you be alſo children of abhomination:</p>
            <p>Oh that you would <hi>forſake her and diſcouer her ſkirts, and teare her in pieces</hi> as ſhe hath deſerued, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to be the children of the Church, and ſeruants of the liuing God! this is that we wiſh you from the Lord, whom we alſo pray that thou whoſoeuer thou art, that wrote this &amp; all other of the faction in the world, may haue grace to perform that which here thou promiſeſt.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:9548:46"/> 
               <hi>No no, though heauen and hell ſhould meete Ile none, Ile none vngracious ſtrumpet get thee gone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, if he will haue none of <hi>Babilons</hi> dainties what wil he haue? for he ſaith he thirſteth, and muſt haue his thirſt quenched, but how?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quench me with bloud ſweet ſonne, with milk good mother</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas theſe are children of Babilon, they will not be healed: for loe he ſings his old ſong againe, he muſt haue <hi>bloud,</hi> he muſt haue <hi>milke:</hi> loe heere the <hi>hunger &amp; thirſt</hi> of a Papiſt, it is for <hi>milke</hi> as well as <hi>bloud:</hi> out Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour proclaymeth to the world, <hi>bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe.</hi> I would heere aske <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 5.</note> a reaſonable Papiſt, a briefe queſtion, whether this righteouſneſſe can be attained by any meanes, but by the <hi>bloud</hi> of the Mediator: If he thinke it may, let him that ſaith ſo, take time to conſider of it, and he will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere otherwiſe: But if not (as if Chriſtians they muſt needs anſwere) then what a kind of thirſt is that, that thirſteth for the <hi>milke</hi> of a creature, as well as for the <hi>bloud</hi> of the Mediator: but whilſt they take time to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere this queſtion, let vs go forward, and trace this Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit to his vnhappy iournyes end.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dic matri meus his frater ſitit optima mater</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vis de fonte</hi> tuo <hi>promere, de que</hi> meo?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dic nato, meus his frater mi mellee fili,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Captiuus monſtra a vincula, litron habes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo redemptorem monſtra te iure vocari</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nobilior reliquis ſi tibi</hi> ſanguis <hi>in eſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tuque parens monſtra matrem te iure vocari,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vbera <hi>ſi reliquis diuitiora geris.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:9548:47"/>
            <p>That is,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Say to thy mother ſee my brothers thirſt,</l>
               <l>Mother, your <hi>milke</hi> will eaſe him at the firſt:</l>
               <l>Say to thy ſonne, behold thy brothers bands,</l>
               <l>Sweet ſonne thou haſt his ranſome in thy hands.</l>
               <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou Sonne,</hi> if that thy <hi>bloud</hi> excell the reſt:</l>
               <l>And ſhew thy ſelfe iuſtly ſo ſtilde indeed,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou mother</hi> if thy <hi>breſts</hi> the reſt exceed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now if you pleaſe to obſerue a little, you ſhall ſee a new peece of Popiſh deuotion: his ground already <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayd is, that he muſt haue <hi>milke</hi> from the mother: <hi>bloud</hi> of the ſonne.</p>
            <p>But how will he come by them? hee hath found a ready way, he will make the Sonne <hi>mediator</hi> to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the mother to her Sonne: <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> hath euer taught, that the Sonne is our <hi>Mediator</hi> to the Father: and <hi>Popiſh Religion</hi> hath long taught that the Mother is a Mediator to her Son: But now they begin to reach that the <hi>ſon is alſo a mediator to his mother:</hi> what will it come to in the end?</p>
            <p>And heere obſerue, that as euer heeretofore when there was any honour in precedence, the <hi>mother</hi> had the firſt place: ſo now when it is a burden and a duty, the <hi>ſonne</hi> muſt haue it, but not till then, for ſo now hee ſaith.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Say to thy mother ſee thy brothers thirſt,</l>
               <l>Mother your milke will eaſe him at the firſt.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:9548:47"/>
            <p>Firſt indeed hee intreates the Son and then the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but what intreates he him? to be a meanes: to whom? to his Mother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for what? for her <hi>milke:</hi> ſo that vpon the matter, her Milke is it that is firſt in his thoughts, its that hee longs for principally, and Chriſt Ieſus ſhall be preferred to goe a meſſage to his mother and to intreate for him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat hee may haue it: as tho he had ſaid, O Ieſus my ſoule ſo thirſts for <hi>milke,</hi> that I cannot be without it: now becauſe thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked me for my preſumption, in offering to take it as boldly as thy <hi>bloud:</hi> I haue therefore no other way but to intreate thee to bee a meanes to thy mother, that ſo by thy mediation and her mercy I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, therefore I beſeech thee Ieſus <hi>ſay to thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> honoured and well aduanced by Popery that makes him mediator to a woman for her <hi>milke,</hi> and for the benefits and merits of it, and that for ſuch a one as will not be content with the benefits and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of his owne <hi>bloud ſhedding:</hi> But behold good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly what diuinity heere is! <hi>A Chriſtian man in his deuotion may</hi> (ſaith this Ieſuite) <hi>deſire Ieſus Chriſt to go intreate his mother for him, &amp; to compaline that his poore brothers ſoule thirſteth, deſiring her to quench and comfort him with her milke:</hi> what is this we heare? Is Chriſt a mediator to a creature? and for ſomething in that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to quench the ſpirituall thirſt of the ſoule? If this be true, then what meant Chriſt to ſay, <hi>Come vnto mee all that bee weary, and I will eaſe you:</hi> for if hee ſend <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 11</note>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:9548:48"/> them that be thirſty and weary to his mother to bee ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſurely in that word, Chriſt either ſpake too much of <hi>himſelfe,</hi> or too little of his <hi>Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Chriſt held that they might come onely to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, then it appeares the Ieſuits Religion and his bee contrary: if he knew that they might come to <hi>her,</hi> as well as <hi>him,</hi> or to her by him, then what meant hee to ſay <hi>Come vnto me,</hi> and not rather <hi>Come vnto her or vnto me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> what can they, what dare they ſay? was hee vndu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to his mother? or enuied hee her dignity, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got he her when he thus ſpake? or was hee ſwayed with too much ſelfe-loue? If none of theſe without blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my may be imagined, then what may be ſaid, that there were any ſuch thing due to her, and hee knew it not? If this alſo be impoſſible, then there remaines but one, that he named himſelfe, but <hi>excluded</hi> not his mother, he bids come to him, and forbids not to come to her: I anſwere, firſt heere he bids vs come to himſelfe, let them ſhew where he bids vs goe to <hi>her,</hi> if he no where bid it, it is as good as forbidden: aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, hee that in <hi>one caſe</hi> of truth ſaid, <hi>I and my Father are one,</hi> would not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 30.</note> haue ſpared in <hi>this caſe</hi> if it had been true, to haue ſayd <hi>I and my mother are one,</hi> and he who out of his holy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and knowing the difference of the fathers dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his owne humanity, freely confeſſed <hi>my father is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>greater then I,</hi> would neuer haue ſcorned (if it had been true) to haue acknowledged, <hi>my mother is as great as I:</hi> whereas contrariwiſe, leauing ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world, he ſaith directly, <hi>Come vnto me:</hi> And whereas he came to <hi>fulfill all righteouſnes:</hi> and the fift <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 15.</note>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:9548:48"/> commaundement wee know commands as well reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Parents, as obedience: therefore doubtleſſe he <hi>who went home</hi> ſaith the text <hi>and was obedient to them,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> would alſo moſt readily haue yeelded her this reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce if it had bene due vnto her, or if it might lawfully haue beene giuen her: But he knowing the contrary, doth in this caſe paſſe by her, and commands <hi>Come vnto mee:</hi> If yet they will reply and ſay, he ſaith indeede come to him, but meaning to ſend vs from himſelfe to <hi>her</hi> for eaſe and comfort, who is the <hi>Mother of mercy and grace:</hi> I anſwere ſo indeede, is ſhe called in their ſeruice book, <note place="margin">Maria mater grati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: mater miſerecordiae: tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nos ab hoſte Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ege, &amp; hora mortis, ſuſcipe. Officium beatae mariae.</note> but God in this booke takes that name to himſele only, and giues it to no creature, therefore let them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere it that giue it to her: Againe, the ground of this re-plication is falſe, for as hee ſaith <hi>Come to mee,</hi> and names no other, ſo neither ſends he vs <hi>to her</hi> for eaſe, but ſaith plainely and directly, <hi>and I will eaſe you.</hi> Further, they not onely make Chriſt a Mediator to his Mother, and that for ſpirituall eaſe and comfort, but they do it in ſuch a faſhion, as they make Chriſt one that either is not able or not willing to helpe vs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: for it he were, then why doe they ſay, that he complaines to his mother, that <hi>we thirſt</hi> &amp; for the eaſe of our ſoules deſires her to <hi>yeeld her milke?</hi> If heere they were asked this queſtion, I wonder how they would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere it? If Chriſt be not willing or nor able to eaſe the thirſty ſoule, then how is he a perfect Sauiour? If hee bee, then how is it likely that hee would ſend him that humbleth his ſoule to him for helpe, to another to be eaſed, ſeeing hee asketh of him, who ſaid, <hi>Come</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:9548:49"/> 
               <hi>vnto me all that are weary,</hi> doth he aske that that Chriſt hath to giue, and is it likely that hee will deny it? doth he aske that that Chriſt hath no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to giue, and is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that his mother hath it? then they may as well ſay that ſhe hath more grace and mercy, or more power &amp; ability then Chriſt himſelf hath: let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwer theſe queſtions, how they will, heere will bee found ſtrange diuinity, which we ſee is curra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the Romiſh Church.</p>
            <p>But whilſt they prepare their anſwere, let it pleaſe the reader to obſerue how contrary the Romiſh doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine is to the doctrine of Chriſt, and of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe as man.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Romiſh doct. makes him ſay.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>My father is greater then I <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14. 28</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>My mother is in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects greater then I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Chriſt ſaith of himſelf as God</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Romiſh dost. makes him ſay.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I and my <hi>Father</hi> are one. <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 30.</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>I and my mother are one.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Chriſt ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Romiſh doctrine makes him ſay.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Come to mee all that are weary, I will eaſe you. <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28.</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Come to me &amp; I will ſend you to <hi>my mother</hi> for eaſe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The ſcripture ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Romiſh doctrine ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſt is the mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>God and man.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5.</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Chriſt is the Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Man and Mary.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The ſcripture ſaith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>They make him ſay.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>No man commeth to the <hi>father</hi> but by me. <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14, 6</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>No man commeth to my <hi>mother</hi> but by me.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:9548:49"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>The ſcripture ſaith</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>They make him ſay.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Whatſoeuer you aske my father in my name hee will giue it you. <note place="margin"> Io. 15. 16</note>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Whatſoeuer you aske my Mother in my name ſhe will giue it you.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like oppoſitions are common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Chriſts Goſpell</hi> and Romiſh diuinity, may not this giue ſtrong ſuſpicion that their Religion is <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian,</hi> which in the foundations of it are ſo repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Chriſts, as theſe and others which ſtand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with more authority then yet theſe doe? well, thus Chriſt is made a Mediator to his Mother, now the Ieſuite proceedeth, and to make him amends, hee maketh the mother a mediator to him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Say to thy Sonne behold my brothers bands,</l>
               <l>Sweete Sonne thou haſt his ranſome in thy hands.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That Chriſt Ieſus hath the <hi>ranſome</hi> of ſinfull ſoules in his hands is good diuinity, and we heartily imbrace it, wiſhing it were as heartily and truly (without Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation) intended by this Papiſt: if he and all other Papiſts do ſo hold it, wee heartily reioyce, but then wee deſire them to anſwere to a few queſtions.</p>
            <p>Who payeth this ranſome? is it not <hi>Chriſt?</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts it? is it not God the <hi>father?</hi> is it not mercy, grace &amp; loue, that either the one will <hi>accept</hi> it, or the other <hi>pay</hi> it? can any pay it but the one? can any take it but the other? are not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains &amp; fathers of mercy, which haue done ſo? if all theſe be true, then what a Religion haue they, who in their liturgies &amp; dayly prayers, call a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:9548:50"/> creature the <hi>mother of mercy, and mother of grace,</hi> oftner then either God the <hi>Father,</hi> or Chriſt the Redeemer, or both put together, we deſire ſome conſcionable papiſt to anſwere vs ſeriouſly: was the Virgin Mary a Creator or a creature? If a creature, was ſhe any more then an excellent creature, ſet apart for the moſt excellent vſe in the world? &amp; was it not in Gods election to haue choſen any other woman, at his owne good pleaſure to haue beene the mother of Chriſt? and was it not his owne free mercy, that <hi>he regarded the low eſtate of her his handmaid?</hi> if this bee ſo, then did ſhee any thing in our ſaluation, which any woman had not done, if God had taken her to be his mother, was there any thing in her to moue God to chuſe her, which was not Gods owne gift in her and to her? ſhe may be then a veſſell of grace, but ſhe can be no way a fountaine of grace: for what had ſhe but ſhe receiued it: but if (as they ſay) ſhe bee the fountaine of mercy and mother of grace, then ſhee giues but receiues not, as the fountaine receiues from no other, but hath of it ſelfe, and ſends out to others: &amp; the mother takes not of her children, but layeth vp for them, Now if it bee as their Liturgie ſaith; it is, that ſhe is the mother of mercy and grace, &amp;c. Then ſure <hi>ſhe hath the ranſome in her hands:</hi> but if it be in Chriſts <hi>hands,</hi> as heere they ſay it is, then how is ſhe the mother of mercy? hardly would theſe bee reconciled, but that they haue equiuocations, reſeruations, or diſtinctions, that will make any thing ſeeme good enough to ſerue their turnes.</p>
            <p>Thus then they haue not only made <hi>Mary</hi> Mediator
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:9548:50"/> to Chriſt, which is common in their Religion, but (which was ſcarce euer heard of before) they make <hi>Chriſt</hi> their mediator to <hi>her,</hi> her to him for his <hi>bloud,</hi> but firſt him to her for her <hi>milke:</hi> Now to leaue this point, obſerue (in one word) how in theſe two meſſages of mediation, heere is no difference, but ſhe that is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſaued by her ſonne, is made to ſpeake to him in the ſame tearmes as he to her, and with no other words or ſignes of reuerence: and her ſonne and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, yea God himſelfe made to ſpeake to her with the ſame reuerence as ſhe doth to him: as though there were no difference betwixt <hi>him</hi> and <hi>her,</hi> and as though he being God and her ſauiour, was as much beholding to her for her <hi>milke,</hi> as ſhee being a creature is to him for his <hi>bloud:</hi> Loe what popiſh deuotion is heere? now if they be aſhamed of this, then why are they not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the other? But they are farre from that, for where are the intreatings, the cryes, the humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and ſubmiſſiue beſeechings to him for his <hi>bloud?</hi> heere be none ſuch: but contrariwiſe as though there were no difference in the world, betwixt either the perſons intreating, which are <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> or the things deſired which be his <hi>bloud</hi> and her <hi>milke,</hi> he ſaith to Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Say to thy mother ſee my brothers thirſt,</l>
               <l>Mother your milke will helpe him at the firſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And to her he ſaith:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Say to thy ſonne behold thy brothers bands,</l>
               <l>Sweete Sonne thou haſt his ranſome in thy hands.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus Popery makes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> one no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:9548:51"/> a perſon then the other, &amp; of his <hi>bloud</hi> and her <hi>milk,</hi> one no greater a matter then the other: <hi>Chriſt</hi> with no more reuerence to bee implored then <hi>Mary,</hi> his <hi>bloud</hi> with no more vehemency to bee deſired, with no more difficulty to be obtained then her <hi>milke:</hi> If this doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine may be defended vnder pretence of deuotion, then will not there want a colour for any blaſphemy: But the Ieſuit goeth forward and ſaith to Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ergo redemptorem monſtra, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou Sonne,</hi> if that thy <hi>bloud</hi> excell the reſt:</l>
               <l>And ſhew thy ſelfe iuſtly ſo ſtilde indeed,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou mother</hi> if thy <hi>breſts</hi> the reſt exceed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It may be doubted in whoſe name he ſpeaketh theſe words, whether in <hi>his owne,</hi> to both Chriſt and his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">Hora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellinus Ieſuita in hiſt. laureta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fat.</note> or in <hi>Chriſts name</hi> to his mother, and in hers to him: if in the firſt, they containe <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> if in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>abſurdity:</hi> for if he ſuppoſe the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſaith thus to Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Shew thy redeeming power to ſoules oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Thou ſonne if that thy bloud excell the reſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It is fouly abſurd to imagine that ſhe being ſo dignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſhe is (yea rather as they hold almoſt deified) ſhould make an if, or a queſtion whether Chriſts bloud excell the reſt or no: and much more abſurd is it to make Chriſt ſeeme to be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of of his mothers power and ſtate how great it is: be it more or leſſe. But if ſo be he ſpeak theſe words himſelfe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, then
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:9548:51"/> behold the hainous iniury done to the precious <hi>bloud</hi> of the mediator. Concerning which this wicked papiſt makes as much &amp; equall doubt, whether it excell the <hi>bloud</hi> of other creatures, as he doth: whether the <hi>milke</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> excel the milke of all other women: let all chriſtian men ſhrinke and tremble at ſo great a blaſphemy, for all the learned Papiſts in the world may be chalenged to proue (if they can) out of Gods word and the grounds of religion, that ſhe was any more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another holy woman, (ſauing this prerogatiue, that ſhe was his mother according to the fleſh) or any more then a Saint of God ſanctified by the ſpirit, and ſaued by the <hi>bloud</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe mother ſhee was in regard of his fleſh: or that her milke had any vertue in the world, but to nouriſh the body as doth the milke of other women, their children: for was not hee <hi>a man like vnto vs in all things (ſin excepted)</hi> and if Chriſt take it no preiudice to himſelfe, to be like vnto men, ſhall it be a wrong to her to be like to other women? Nay we dare goe further and aske them, if God haue vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed once in the whole new Teſtament ſo much as to name the milke of the Virgin <hi>Mary?</hi> whereas almoſt in euery Chapter hee extolleth the <hi>bloud</hi> of Chriſt, and is euer magnifying the vertue, merits, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficacy of the ſame: if this bee ſo, then what ſhall we ſay to that Religion and to thoſe men, who make it as queſtionable, whether Chriſt Ieſus his <hi>bloud</hi> excell the bloud of other men, as whether the Virgin Maries <hi>milke</hi> exceede the <hi>milke</hi> of other women? is this Romiſh religion? is this popiſh diuinity? then ſee what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:9548:52"/> But it cannot be proued either to <hi>reaſon</hi> or to <hi>faith</hi> that her <hi>milke</hi> excelleth other womens: in any ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or corporall vertue or operation: therefore it is not to be prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed that Chriſts <hi>bloud</hi> is more precious then other mens: See here my deare countrymen, how you are miſ-led, ſee what doctrine you are fed withall by your teachers! open your eyes and bee no longer deceiued; offer not this iniury to him that gaue his life for you, to make this vnequall compariſon: if they will not teach you holy and ſound diuinity, then hate them, and learne from vs, or rather with vs, from the holy ſcriptures, that <hi>his bloud is the price of our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> but as for her milke wee know no ſuch thing, ſince ſhee liued on earth: acknowledge with vs that it is a fundamentall ground of Chriſtian faith that his <hi>bloud</hi> is more worth then ten worlds: but that her <hi>milke</hi> is now of any vallue, can nether bee perſwaded to reaſon nor beleeued by ſaith: and yet dare this malignant ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoue make that as likely as probable, as certaine as the other: If enemies of Religion take hold heere, and ſay, that therefore the ground, of our Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity are vncertaine, and ſo blaſpheme the bleſſed bloud of our Sauiour, we can ſay no more but our Church is innocent, our hearts are free, our hands are cleere of it: <hi>woe be to them by whom the offence commeth.</hi> But now let us ſee how the Ieſuite concludes, and whether his end be any beter then his beginnning.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O quando lactabor ab vbere, vulnere paſcar!</l>
               <l>delitijſ que fruar, mamma, latuſ que tuis!</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:9548:52"/>
               <l>Parce Deus: magno ſi te clamore fatigem:</l>
               <l>non potis imperio, non poti arte regi,</l>
               <l>Exagitante ſiti, Patientia perdit habenas</l>
               <l>clamores ſi vis tollere, tolle ſitim.</l>
               <l>Pluris ego clauis: ſaturaſti ſanguine clauos</l>
               <l>lanceaque erubuit ſanguine tincta tuo.</l>
               <l>Pluris ego pannis: maduerent vndi que panni</l>
               <l>natia vulneribus, Matris ab vberibus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ah when ſhall I with theſe be ſatisfied,</l>
               <l>when ſhall I ſwim in ioyes of breſt and ſide:</l>
               <l>pardon O God mine eager earneſtneſſe,</l>
               <l>If I thy lawes and reaſons bounds tranſgreſſe,</l>
               <l>Where thirſt ore-ſwayes, Patience is thruſt away:</l>
               <l>ſtay but my thirſt and then my cryes will ſtay,</l>
               <l>Better am I then nayles, yet did aſtreame</l>
               <l>of thy deare <hi>bloud</hi> waſh both the Launce and them:</l>
               <l>More worthy I then clouts, yet them a floud</l>
               <l>moyſtned of Mothers <hi>milke</hi> and of Sonnes <hi>bloud.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Now comes he to his concluſion, but alas his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is as much at the laſt as at the firſt: for ſtill hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in his impiety, without repentance, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce, without ſorrow or ſence of the euill hee hath done, for ſtill he ſings his old ſong:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>O when ſhall I ſuck the milke of theſe breſts, when ſhall I drinke the bloud of theſe wounds.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>His ſoule thirſteth, but for what? for <hi>milke</hi> and for
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:9548:53"/> 
               <hi>bloud:</hi> but firſt for <hi>milke</hi> and then for <hi>bloud:</hi> If this be tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable diuinity, nay if this bee holy deuotion, then what did our bleſſed Sauiour meane to cry out to all weary and thirſty ſoules, <hi>If any man thirſt let him come vnto me and drinke:</hi> I wiſh the Ieſuits would tell vs what they thinke, whether he did well or no, to leaue out the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> for if this diuinity of theirs bee good, then he ought to haue ſaid, <hi>If any man thirſt let him come to my mother or to me to drinke:</hi> and ſurely if her milke be thus equall in vallue, price and merrit to his bloud, then wee doe no longer maruell that they teach how the Virgin Mary did riſe from the dead, and was aſſumed into heauen corporally, that as Chriſt roſe &amp; aſcended to apply &amp; make good the merrit of his death ſo did ſhe alſo to make effectuall the merrit of her milk. But then good <hi>Paul</hi> how farre art thou to blame, that <hi>eſteemeſt all things in the world dunge and droſſe,</hi> and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that thou mighteſt <hi>know the vertue of the reſurrection!</hi> for then it ſeemes, thou wilt giue little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or nothing to know the vertue of her aſſumption: But it may bee thou art halfe an Heretike, and beleeueſt not any ſuch aſſumption: but if thou couldeſt bee taken within the reach of the holy inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou ſhouldſt pay well for ſuch thy hereticall incredulity: If now thou wert aliue thy better and more holy brethren the Ieſuites, could reprooue thee for many indiſcreete paſſages, and teach thee better diuinity then thou ſeemeſt to know, for whereas thou durſt ſay, <hi>thou eſteemedſt to know nothing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 8, 9, 10</note> 
               <hi>but Ieſus Chriſt and him crucified,</hi> they can tell thee thou art farre ſhort in thy duty, and but cold in zeale in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:9548:53"/> of them, for they ſtand in doubt whether to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme now the bloud of his wounds, or the milke of her Paps: and whereas thou wilt giue all to <hi>know the vertue of his reſurrection,</hi> they can but wonder at thy ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, who careſt not to know the vertue of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection &amp; aſcention alſo: Be thou content to know the one, they for their parts will know both: and if thou be ſo preciſe for thy Maſter, that thou canſt not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſay, that <hi>he purgeth our ſins,</hi> but muſt exclude all other, and ſay, that he <hi>by himſelfe</hi> purgeth our ſins: know thou that they dare be ſo bold as to put out that word <hi>by himſelfe</hi> out of the text: and when they reade <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3</note> thy Epiſtles they are halfe aſhamed to ſee what a <hi>blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> man thou art, for thou art all in <hi>bloud, bloud,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as twenty times at leaſt thou art ſtill vpon bloud as though there were no ſaluation but by bloud, and as though bleſſed Maries milke had no merit at all. It ſeemes that as thou wert a perſecutor, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in bloud afore thy conuerſion, ſo thou beares ſtill a bloudy mind: but now behold theſe meeke, &amp; milde and mercifull men (the Ieſuits) a generation that loues no cruelty, nor ſeekes to ſhed no bloud (as moſt nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">Witneſſe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land the Powder treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: In France the laſt Kings death, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent wars in Sweden and broyles in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. &amp;c.</note> of the world can well beare witneſſe) theſe ſweete and gracious fathers being poſſeſſed with a better ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are weary of bloud and do rather chooſe and deſire milke to quench the ſpirituall thirſt of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>If they would vtter what their prophane harts think, or diſcouer openly what they mutter amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, we ſhould here them publiſh euen ſuch diuinity as this is: (a taſte whereof, beſides the preſent poems, you ſhall read anon.)</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:9548:54"/>
            <p>But now for his concluſion, this blaſpheming Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite dare proceede and turne his ſpeech to God and not fearing the commaundement that forbids him to take Gods Name in vaine, vnder paine of ſtanding guilty, at the barre of Gods iuſtice, hee dare offer to abuſe the name of God, with ſuch a prayer as this.</p>
            <p>O Lord thou muſt pardon mee though I cry aloud, for it is not bloud will ſerue my ſoule, I long for milke, and am ſo a thirſt, that I may not keepe ſilence: and why Lord ſhouldeſt thou ſo long keepe me a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ioner in this caſe? I am better then the nayles, yet they had bloud inough: I am not ſo vile as clouts, yet they wanted neither milke nor bloud.</p>
            <p>What kind of men are theſe Ieſuits, or what a God is their God, to whom they dare preſent ſuch a prayer as this? ſurely they thinke as baſely of him as they doe highly of themſelues, or elſe they neuer durſt thus inſult ouer him, &amp; thus abuſe him, as after he hath told them plainely, that <hi>his bloud is drinke indeed,</hi> and commanded <hi>them that are a thirſt to come and drinke of that well of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. 55 <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>of life,</hi> to come and tell him to his face that their ſoules thirſt for milke, &amp; they muſt haue it? belike theſe crawling frogs thinke that they haue ſuch a God as they may leape and play vpon at pleaſure: But O <hi>thou that dwelleſt in heauen langh them to ſcorne, haue them and their wickedneſſe in deriſion:</hi> and either worke them to repentance and viſible conuerſion, or bring them to vengeance and iuſt confuſion.</p>
            <p>The Ieſuite concludes with a compariſon of himſelfe to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:9548:54"/> body, and the cloaths that toucht him in his infancy and death: &amp; indeed the firſt compariſon is not much vnequall, for the Ieſuits are moſt like to nayles &amp; laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Chriſts body; for ſeeing the holy Ghoſt tells vs that wicked men by their ſinnes did and doe pierce Chriſt: then the Ieſuites who by their Atheiſmes, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, periuries, equiuocations, treaſons and manifold impieties, haue beene ſharper nayles and launces in Chriſts body, and greater diſhonorers of his Religion, then any other ſort of men (if the voyce of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; the teſtimony of their owne brethren be true) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Ieſuits I ſay are not vnfitly reſembled to nayles &amp; launces: and indeed they are thornes in the eyes, and pricks in the ſide of all princes and ſtates where they come: leſſe maruell though they be like the nailes and ſpeare in Chriſts body! therefore let the Ieſuit pleaſe himſelfe in this compariſon, as long as he will, we enuy it not.</p>
            <p>But for the ſecond, that hee is better then the clothes that were about theſe two bleſſed bodies, I ſay but this: that either the Ieſuits are farre more holy then the Prophet Eſay, or els he farre more humble in his owne eyes then they: for he profeſſeth in his owne &amp; the churches name, that they were no better then the filthieſt clout that euer was, <hi>euen a menſtruous cloth,</hi> But ſaith the Ieſuit, I am better then the beſt cloth that euer was: for though wee hold that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen laſting vertue to his Word and Sacraments but none that we know to rags, or clouts: yet we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:9548:55"/> that as farre as clothes may one excell mother thoſe that touched the bodies of our Loid and his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are the moſt precious, and if we could be ſure wee had them, we would eſteeme them aboue cloth of gold: we therefore wonder how a man comming before the Lord his God, dare in his prayer make himſelfe better then thoſe clothes, eſpecially hearing the Prophet cry before him, O Lord all our righteouſneſſe is like a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous clout. If our beſt be ſo filthy, what is our nature, what is our ſin? if he anſwer that this is but a cauill, for he meanes that he being a man he is therefore capable of grace and ſaluation, which the cloathes are not, I thinke ſo alſo: But why then doth hee enuy that milke and bloud ſhould touch them? If he meane the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall and reall <hi>milke</hi> and <hi>bloud</hi> that were in the bodies of Chriſt and his mother, then he is more then mad, to enuy the nayles, the launce, the clouts, for that they did touch them, and yet he cannot, and if he complaine that he may not, we aske him why then did not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles take more carefull order to gather vp and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that <hi>milke</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> or if they did not, at leaſt why did they not complaine of the want of them, as he doth heere? ſurely either they had too little <hi>deuotion,</hi> or the Icluirs too much <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if he meane the vertue, merit and efficacy of the <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>milke,</hi> then let him anſwere vs two ſhort queſtions. Firſt, what ſpirituall vertue and power had that milke, what did it worke in our ſaluation, (more then the milke of another woman could) what did it merrit for vs? what the <hi>bloud</hi> did we know and moſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:9548:55"/> willingly do acknowledge: but what the <hi>milk</hi> did or can do, if the Ieſuites can tell and teach vs, wee will not refuſe to learne: But ſuppoſing that it had as much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue as the <hi>bloud</hi> (as the Ieſuite affirmes, but farre be it from vs once ſo to thinke) then ſecondly wee aske him whether he thinke the Nayles, Launce, and Clouts, were partakers of the vertue and merrit of that bloud, if he do, let him ſhew where he receiued ſuch diuinity: if not, then to what end complaines he to God in ſuch a faſhion.</p>
            <p>Lord I am better then the Nayles and Clouts, and yet they had Bloud and Milke inough, but I dye for thirſt.</p>
            <p>If this be not to take Gods name in vaine, and that in a high meaſure, we appeale to all Chriſtian men of reaſonable iudgement.</p>
            <p>And thus at laſt are we come to an end of this Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Goſpell, the impiety whereof I now remit to the cenſure of the Chriſtian world.</p>
            <p>And for my concluſion, leaſt any ſhould ſay that this is but one priuate Ieſuits deede, and therefore may not preindice the whole ſociety of Ieſuits, and much leſſe the Religion of Popery.</p>
            <p>To theſe I anſwere, 1. the booke is allowed and hath beene twiſe printed, and ſtands approued by <hi>Poſſeuine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Poſſeu. in appar. ſee lit, C</note> amongſt good and catholike authors. 2. Let them ſhew what Ieſuite or other popiſh doctor hath <hi>reprooued,</hi> or what Inquiſitor or other popiſh Magiſtrate hath cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this wickedneſſe. 3. Which is worſt of all, it is no more in effect then others of them haue taught or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:9548:56"/> though not in ſo open, apparant, and foule a faſhion, for let any Chriſtian man iudge what diuinity is laid downe in theſe points that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The papiſts haue a book called the <hi>Mariale,</hi> It hath beene obiected vnto them that in this booke it is thus <note place="margin">
                  <hi>This hath beene long agoe laid to their charge in Catalogo, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um veritatis editionis</hi> 1609.</note> ſaid: Salomon ſaith <hi>the name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower</hi> Pro. 18. 10. But <hi>Salomon</hi> knew little of the Virgin Mary, let vs therefore ſay, <hi>the name of our Lady is a ſtrong tower,</hi> let the ſinner flye vnto her, and he ſhall be ſaued: and againe: thou art a ſinner, flye then to the name of Mary, that alone ſhall ſerue to heale thee: and againe:</p>
            <p>The Lord was with Mary, and Mary with the Lord, in the ſame labour and ſame worke of our redemption for the Mother of mercy helped the Father of mercy, in the worke of our ſaluation: and thereupon was it ſpoken of the firſt woman, <hi>It is not good for man to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, let vs make him a helper:</hi> But why then ſaith God, Eſay 63. <hi>I haue troden the wine preſſe alone, and of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there was no man with me:</hi> the booke anſwereth, it is true Lord that thou ſayeſt, there was no man with thee but there was a woman with thee, which bore all the wounds in her heart, that thou didſt beare in thy body.</p>
            <p>Loe heere a peece of rare diuinitie! Salomon is blamed for ignorance, that he knew but little of the Virgin, &amp; in a ſort is rebuked for ſaying <hi>the name of our Lord,</hi> and not rather the name of our Lady <hi>is a ſtrong tower:</hi> and though no man did, yet a woman (namely Mary) did helpe Chriſt to treade the winepreſſe of Gods wrath, and was fellow worker with God, in the worke of our redemption.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:9548:56"/>
            <p>This booke ſtands vnconfuted, vncondemned, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reproued by the Ieſuits or the Romiſh Church, till this day for ought that I can yet find, yet hath it beene many yeeres laid to their charge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Againe the Papiſts haue a booke, they call it the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Pſalter, printed at Paris in the yeere 1520. or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Pſalterium beate Virgini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Maria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum cum Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terio Ciſtercienſi Par. circa anno</hi> 1520. <hi>Extat e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam idem. Pſal. ad verbum, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Chem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in examine concil Trident: in parte</hi> 3. <hi>P.</hi> 149 <hi>editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis franco furt.</hi> 1996.</note> wherein euery one of the 150. Pſalmes are in whole or in part turned from <hi>dominus</hi> to <hi>domina,</hi> that is, from God our Chriſt to our Lady, as</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the firſt Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> Bleſſed is the man that loueth thy name O Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 19. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> The Heauens declare thy glory O Virgin Mary, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 29 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> Bring vnto our Lady O you mighty bring vnto our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy worſhip and honour, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ine</hi> 51 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> Haue mercy vpon me O Lady, thou that art called the Mother of mercy, and according to the bowels of thy mercies, clenſe me from all my ſinnes, poure out thy grace vpon me, and take not thy wonted mercy from me, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 57 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> Haue mercy vpon me O Lady, haue mercy vpon me, for my heart ie ready to ſearch out thy will, and in the ſhadow of thy wings will I reſt.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 68 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> Let our Lady ariſe, and her enemies ſhall be ſcattered, &amp;c.</q>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:9548:57"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 72. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> Lord giue thy iudgement to the King, and thy mercy to our Lady his mother.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 94 <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> God is the God of reuenge, but thou O Lady the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy, doeſt bow him to take pitty, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 96. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> O ſing vnto our Lady a new long, for ſhee hath done maruailous things, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 110. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lord ſaid vnto our Lady, ſit thou mother at my right hand, &amp;c,</q>
            <p>Thus I might go ouer all the Pſalmes, but as he began he ends in the laſt words of the laſt Pſalme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let euery thing that hath breath prayſe our Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this booke ſtands not onely vncontrolled, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. de val in vol. de rebus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei controuerſis, ſect.</hi> 5. <hi>lib de Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latria</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Bernar. de Buſtis in Mariali parte</hi> 3. <hi>ſer.</hi> 3</note> rather euen defended by the Ieſuits, and thoſe of the principall.</p>
            <p>3 Againe, a famous Fryer &amp; well approued amongſt them, preacht this doctrine in the pulpit (amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, little better.)</p>
            <p>A man may appeale from God himſelfe to the Vitgin Mary, if any man feele himſelfe grieued at the iuſtice of God, ſeeing God hath deuided his kingdome with her, for whereas God hath iuſtice and mercy, he hath reſerued iuſtice to himſelfe, to bee exerciſed in this world as it pleaſed him: but mercy hee hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his mother: If therefore any man find himſelfe agrieued in the court of Gods iuſtice, let him appeale to the court of mercy, of his mother.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:9548:57"/>
            <p>This Diuinity was ſo well reliſht in the Romiſh Church, that after hee had preacht it, he publiſht it vnder the Popes owne Patronage: and the booke was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexan. the</hi> 6.</note> againe printed within theſe three yeeres: but what ſay the Ieſuits to it, they teſtifie that this booke, is a learned and godly book, full of goodneſſe and piety.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Horatius Turcellinus,</hi> himſelfe a Ieſuit of <note place="margin">Horatius Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellinus: in Hiſt. virg. lauretan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fat.</note> good eſteeme among them, writes thus.</p>
            <p>Almighty God hath made the Virgin his mother, as far as he may lawfully, partaker of his diuine power and Maieſty.</p>
            <p>Now ſurely if God haue made her fellow with him of his diuine maieſty, leſſe maruell if Chriſt haue made her fellow in the worke of redemption. And this booke <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſſeu. in lit.</hi> 11.</note> written by a Ieſuit, hath publike allowance, and is dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Cardinall <hi>Aldobrandino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, a great Spaniſh Doctor, and profeſſor of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity of his order, writes thus.</p>
            <p>We haue often ſeene and heard of very many who in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn Chryſoſt. a viſitatione, de verbis dominae to</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2</note> their extreame dangers haue called vpon Mary and preſently were deliuered: for oft times ſafety is ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner obtained by calling vpon the name of Mary, then by calling vpon the name of Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>And this booke is both dedicated to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the <note place="margin">Poſſeu. in appera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu ſacro lit. l.</note> 8. &amp; receiues publike allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by the Ieſuits: his name is <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> as tho hee were a golden mouthed ſpeaker: but if thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his doctrine, that her mediation is as powerfull, or rather more then is her ſonnes, it is pitty but he ſhould be call'd and accounted a leaden
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:9548:58"/> mouthed wretch:</p>
            <p>By all theſe &amp; many more that (as the learned know) might eaſily be produced, it may appeare that this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming Ieſuit <hi>Bonarſcius,</hi> in this his deteſtable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, of her milke with Chriſts bloud, ſaith no more in effect then others both of this Religion and perticular ſect, and therefore it may be iuſtly concluded, this is the doctrine and diuinity not of him alone, but of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, and of the popiſh Church it ſelfe, as long as it ſtands approued or not condemned by them: Now then if this be the diuinity of the Romiſh Church.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That a Creatures milke may bee mingled with Chriſts bloud in the matter &amp; merit of our ſaluation.</item>
               <item>2 That it helps and heales ſpirituall ſores of the ſoule as well as the bloud.</item>
               <item>3 That though no man did, yet a woman did help Chriſt in the worke of our ſaluation.</item>
               <item>4 That the Pſalmes may bee turned from Lord to Lady.</item>
               <item>5 That a man may appeale from God to the Virgin Mary.</item>
               <item>6 That God hath deuided his kingdome with her, keeping Iuſtice to himſelfe, and ſurrendring Mercy to her.</item>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:9548:58"/>
               <item> 7. That God hath made her pertaker with himſelfe of his diuine power and Maieſty.</item>
               <item>8. That a mans prayers are often heard, rather by and through her, then Chriſt Ieſus.</item>
            </list>
            <p>If theſe I ſay be the doctrines of the preſent Church of Rome, then let the Chriſtian world be pleaſed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue,</p>
            <list>
               <item n="1">1. How far the preſent Romiſh Church, is degenerate from the ancient.</item>
               <item n="2">2. How great cauſe we and all Churches of God haue to ſeperate from ſuch a ſinagogue.</item>
               <item n="3">3. How iuſtly they may be pronounced Antichriſtian. who thus hainouſly diſparage the Perſon and office of the Mediator.</item>
               <item n="4">4. How vntrue is it that by any ſuggeſtion, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Religion of Rome is much reformed and refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at this day: for it is moſt certaine in the former times theſe would haue beene condemned as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies euen in the Romiſh Church it ſelfe.</item>
               <item>And laſtly you of this moſt honorable City, eſpecially you the Lord Maior, and your brethren, being one moſt worthy renowned Benches of the world, one of the greateſt glories of this land, may here ſee what
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:9548:59"/> cauſe there is to hold the true Papiſts Hereticks, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the preſent Church holds not only theſe but many other fundamentall errors, both for matter of faith, and of gouernment: which ſhewes them not only enemies to all true religion, but the ſubuerters, or at leaſt the vnderminers of all ciuill ſtates in the world, wherein they were euer ſuffered.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And conſidering that all meanes hath beene vſed, to reclaime and reforme her, but all is in vaine, (for ſhe is that <hi>Babilon that will not be healed)</hi> wherefore it is our duty to forſake her &amp; leaue her to the iuſt hand of God.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall wee follow the counſell of the Prophet in like caſe who ſaith: <hi>We would haue healed Babilon, but ſhe would not be healed: let vs forſake her and goe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man to his owne Country, for he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iudgement is come vp to Heauen and lifted vp to the Clouds.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9548:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
